<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE website PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/website/2.5.0/schema/dtd/website-full.dtd">

<webpage id="faq" lang="en">

    <head>
        <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
        <titleabbrev>FAQ</titleabbrev>
        <summary>Frequently Asked Questions</summary>
    </head>


    <qandaset>
        <?dbhtml toc="1" ?>  
        <?dbhtml cellspacing="3px" cellpadding="3px" ?> 

        <qandadiv>
            <title >General/ Unsorted</title>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>When is an auto-installation problem really  AutoYaST related?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>If you have issues during auto-installing a client it does not
                        always mean that it is autoyast related. AutoYaST relies on many
                        general installation components and thus, some problems might be
                        general installation problems. During auto-installation, almost all
                        problems perior the start of yast2 are linuxrc related. For example,
                        if the installation source can't be found, then you have to check the
                        kernel command line variables, (i.e. install) which are used by
                        linuxrc to fetch the installation image (boot/root).</para>

                    <para>If yast2 starts and a problem occurs, most likely it is an
                        autoyast issue and has to be reported as such. The control file is
                        retrieved by yast2 and not by linuxrc as with releases perior to
                        8.0.</para>

                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>

                    <para>How can I include external and remote files into the profile in
                        runtime, i.e. during installation?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>You can do that using XML XInclude. XInclude is an emerging W3C
                        specification for building large XML documents out of multiple
                        well-formed XML documents, independently of validation. Each piece
                        can be a complete XML document, a fragmentary XML document, or a
                        non-XML text document like a Java program or an e-mail message.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        XInclude reference external documents to be included with include
                        elements in the http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude namespace. The
                        prefix xi is customary though not required. Each xi:include element
                        has an href attribute that contains a URL pointing to the file to
                        include. For example, if you want to have all scripts out of the
                        main profile, you can have them on a remote machine or make them
                        available on the machine being installed and reference them from
                        within the control file. Note that the profile is parsed only once
                        at the beginning of the installation, so the scripts have to be
                        available during initial system and autoinstallation setup.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The following is a section of a profile showing the scripts section:
                    </para>

                    <programlisting>
                        <xi:include href="xinclude_scrips.xml" parse="text"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>
                    </programlisting>
                    <para>On the remote side, which is in this case a web server, you
                        will have the included version in a file
                        <filename>chroot_sh.xml</filename> which will contain the missing
                        portion you want to include, for example:</para>

                    <programlisting>
                        <xi:include href="xinclude_scrips_contents.xml" parse="text"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>
                    </programlisting>
                    <para>
                        When including complex portions of the control file, you have
                        to pay attention to adding the namespace to the included file.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para >Is there any way to define IP ranges in rules?</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>
                        Range is not supported for IPs. To make that happen with 9.0 however,
                        you can always use you own script in the rules which you can
                        match. For example I can use this rule to match the boardinfo of my old
                        thinkpad:
                    </para>


                    <programlisting>
                        <xi:include href="boardinfo.xml" parse="text"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>
                    </programlisting>




                    <para>So you have to write a script that will output the latest segment of an IP and do a range checking, i,e, on 210-240.</para>

                    <para>so it will result in something like that(not tested):</para>

                    <programlisting>
                        <xi:include href="networkrange.xml" parse="text"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>
                    </programlisting>

                    <para>
                        Of course you can add other rules such as these to match the subnet and the
                        network, etc.
                    </para>


                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>
                        Do I really have to write all the scripts inside a profile? Is it not
                        possible to just call an external script file? </para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>
                        Well, you can call an external script from the script themselves,
                        however, you have to make the scripts available to the system somehow
                        and the easiest solution is to include the scripts into the control
                        file. 
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>Is there a length limit on the line of parameters passed to
                        linuxrc using the boot menu (kernel command line)?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>Yes, there is a limit, I am not sure what is it though (someone telling me it is 256).</para>

                    <para>To avoid this, use an <emphasis>info</emphasis> file
                        with all parameters. Make sure all the URLs to the
                        installation source and to the profile are short. Use
                        symlinks or aliases instead of specifying the complete
                        path. Any keyword on the command line that is beyond
                        the allowed length will be ommited.
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>How does YaST know a URL is actually a directory and
                    not a file name?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>To make YaST retrieve the control file from a
                        directory, i.e. by naming the control file with the
                        hex IP (for example C0A80103) and to make it default to
                        a file named <filename>default</filename> in that
                        directory, you have to add the trailing slash,
                    </para>
                    <example>
                        <title>Path to a directory</title>
                        <screen>
autoyast=http://192.168.1.1/profiles/
                        </screen>
                    </example>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

        </qandadiv>






        <qandadiv>
            <title>SuSE Linux Enterprise Server 8</title>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>How to use updates and bug fixes during installation of SLES SP3?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>All fixes are provided in the driverupdate image available with
                        SP3. One has to make sure the file or the contents of the file
                        (linux subdirectory) is available in the root of the source.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>Is there a need to patch or update the GA root image ( boot/root on the CD) with SP3?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>No, All fixes are already provided in the driverupdate file.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>HTTP/FTP Installation does not work with SLES8 GA, whats wrong?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>This is a known issue with SLES8 and is a general problem and
                        not autoyast related. This is issue has been resolved with
                        SP3. Make sure you have the driverupdate in the root of the source
                        and boot using the kernel/initrd from SP3.</para>

                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>Is it possible to skip the license agreement for UL based
                        products while setting up the system via autoinstall?</para>

                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para> Use SLES8 SP3 kernel, initrd and driverupdate.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <!--
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>Can I create an installation source by loop mounting ISO images
                        instead of copying them to the local disk?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>Yes. It is possible only if you install using FTP or HTTP. For NFS
                        Installations you have to use the user-space nfs server. (Kernel
                        NFS would also work, but you have to create export enteries for
                        every loop mount and then you have to mount them on the client individually)</para>
                    <para>The following example shows how this can be
                        accomplished:</para>

                    <programlisting>
                        <xi:include href="xinclude_multiplesource.xml" parse="text"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>
                    </programlisting>
                    <para>NOTE that the symlinks in the root of the install server remain the
                        same for a different service pack. You still need the boot information from
                        SP3, and the pointers to media.1 and content from base SLES work
                        fine. (<ulink
                            url="http://lists2.suse.com/archive/suse-autoinstall/2004-Feb/0007.html">credits</ulink>)
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            -->
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>How do I update kernel modules during installation?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>
                        This is a general issue and can also be used when installing manually.
                    </para>
                    <para>The process of creating driver updates and adding new modules is
                        described in the <ulink
                            url="ftp://ftp.suse.com/pub/people/hvogel/Update-Media-HOWTO/Update-Media-HOWTO.html">Update Media Howto</ulink></para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
        </qandadiv>

    </qandaset>
</webpage>
