
  <chapter id="Configuration">
    <title>
      System Configuration 
    </title>
    <para>
      The system configuration during auto-installation can be seen as the
      most important part of the whole process. Customizing a system to your
      environment needs is what makes an auto-installation system attractive,
      not the installation part.
    </para>
    <para>
      As you have seen in the previous chapters, almost anything can be
      configured automatically on the target system. In addition to the
      pre-defined directives, you can always  use post-scripts to change other
      things in the system. Additionally you can change any system variables and
      if required, copy complete configuration files into the target system.
    </para>
    <sect1>
      <title>
	Post-Install and System Configuration
      </title>
      <para>
	The Post-Installation and the System Configuration are initiated directly after the last
	package is installed in the target system  and is continued after the
	system has booted for the first time.
      </para>
      <para>
	Before the system is booted for the first time, &yast2; writes all data
	collected during installation into the system and finally it writes the
	boot loader in the specified location. In addition to these regular
	tasks, which are also done when performing a normal installation, YaST2
	executed the <emphasis>chroot-scripts</emphasis> as specified in the
	control file. Note that these scripts are executed while the system is
	still not mounted.
      </para>      
      <para>
	If a different kernel than the default is installed, a hard reboot will
	be required. A hard reboot can also be forced during auto-installation,
	independent of the installed kernel. This can be accomplished using the
	<emphasis>reboot</emphasis> property of the
	<emphasis>general</emphasis> resource. (See <link
	  linkend="CreateProfile.General">General Options</link>)
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>System Customization</title>
      <para>
	Most of the system customization is done in the second stage of the
	installation. &yast2; provides most of the important resources needed to
	bring up  a system to a usable , general state. However, you may have
	other requirements for the installed system. If the required
	customizations can't be done using &yast2; resources, then the
	post-install scripts can be used to accomplish this task.
      </para>
      <para>
	You can define an unlimited number of custom scripts in the control
	file either by editing the control file or by using the configuration
	system.	
      </para>      
    </sect1>

    
  </chapter>


  <!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: xml
  sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "part")
  End:
  -->
  