 <sect1 id="CreateProfile.CMS">
  <title>
    Using the Configuration Management System
  </title>  
  <para>
    In order to create the control file for a specific computer, a &yast2;
    based system is provided. This system depends on existing modules
    which are usually used to configure a computer in regular operation mode,
    i.e. after &company-suse; Linux is installed.
  </para>
  <para>
    The configuration management system lets you create control files easily and
    additionally it lets you manage a repository of configurations for use
    in a networked environment and with multiple clients.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Configuration System</title>
    <mediaobject>&cms-configuration-type;</mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <sect2 id="Classes">
    <title>
      Using Classes and Templates
    </title>
    <simplesect>
    <para>
      Using the configuration management system, you can define a set of
      classes. The class definition consists  of the following variable for each class:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>	        
	  Name: Class name
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>	    
	  Descriptions: Class description
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>	        
	  Order: Order (or priority) of the class in the stack of migration
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <figure>
      <title>Defining Classes</title>
      <mediaobject>&cms-class-definitions;</mediaobject>	  
    </figure>
    <para>
      You can create as many classes as required, however it is
      recommended to keep the set of classes as small as possible to keep the
      configuration system concise. As an example, the following set of
      classes can be used:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  site: Classes describing a physical location or site.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>machine: Classes describing a type of machine or make</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>role: Classes describing the function of the machine to be installed</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>group: Classes describing a department or a group within a site or a location.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      A  file defined in a class can have the same syntax and format as the
      regular control file and represents a subset of the configuration. For example,
      to create a new control file  for a special computer with a specific network
      interface, only the resource in the control file, which control
      the configuration of the network are needed. Having multiple network
      types, you can merge the one needed for a special type of hardware
      with other class files and thus, creating a new control file which
      corosponds to the defined classes.
    </para>

    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Templates</title>
      
    </simplesect>
  </sect2>
</sect1>



      <!--
       Local Variables:
       mode: xml
       sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "sect1")
       End:
      -->
