  <chapter id="configuration">
    <title>Configuration and Installation Options</title>
    <para>
      This chapter introduces important parts of a control file for
      standard purposes. To have an idea about the other options available,
      use the configuration management system.     
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that for some of the configuration options to work, additional
      packages have to be installed, depending on the software selection you
      have configured. If you choose to install <emphasis>Minimal</emphasis>
      then some packages might be missing and those have to be added to the
      individual package selection.
    </para>
    <para>
      YaST will install packages required by YaST modules in the second phase
      of the installation and before the post-installation phase of AutoYaST
      has started, however if the YaST modules are not available in the
      system, this will not happen. For example, no security settings will be
      configured if <emphasis>yast2-security</emphasis> is not installed.
    </para>
    <section id="CreateProfile.General">
      <title id="CreateProfile.General.title">
	General Options
      </title>
      
      <para>
	General
	options include all the settings related to the installation process and
	the environment of the installed system. Among
	others it includes the following 4 properties which are required:
	<emphasis>language</emphasis>,<emphasis> keyboard</emphasis>,<emphasis>
	  clock</emphasis> and <emphasis>mouse</emphasis> almost for any
	installation. If left out, default values will be used, which might not
	be in one hand with what you want.
	
      </para>
      <example>
	<title>General Options</title>
	<screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.generalOptions.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>	  
	</screen>
      </example>      

  
  <para>
    By default, the auto-installation process has to be confirmed by the
    user. The confirmation should be disabled if a fully unattended
    installation is desired. This option is used to view and change the
    settings on a target system before anything is committed and can be
    used for debugging. It is set to <emphasis>true</emphasis> by default
    to avoid recursive installs when the system schedules a reboot after
    initial system setup.
  </para>
  <para>
     With <emphasis>halt</emphasis> you make autoyast to turn off the machine
     after all packages have been installed. So instead of the reboot into
     stage two, the machine is turned off. The bootloader is alreay installed
     and all your chroot scripts have run.
  </para>
     <note>
	<title>Change starting from SUSE Linux 9.1/SLES 9</title>
	<para>
	  The <emphasis>reboot</emphasis> property in the <emphasis>mode</emphasis>
	  resource was used to force a reboot after initial system setup and before
	  the system is booted for the first time. Currently after initial installation
	  all systems must boot, which makes this option obsolete.
	</para>	
      </note>
      <note>
	<title>SLES9 Only Options</title>
	<para>In SLES 9, it is possible to halt the system after the initial
	  installation phase using the boolean property <emphasis>halt</emphasis></para>
      </note>  
     <note>
	<title>Change starting from SUSE Linux 10.1/SLES10</title>
	<para>
	  The <emphasis>language</emphasis>, <emphasis>keyboard</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>clock</emphasis> properties in the <emphasis>general</emphasis>
	  resource were moved to the root (<emphasis>profile</emphasis>) element of
      the autoyast profile. So don't use them in the general section anymore.
	</para>
    <para>
      Since now you can use the <emphasis>second_stage</emphasis> property, which
      can turn off autoyast after the first reboot. So the complete second stage is
      a manual installation (default is true, which means that autoyast is doing a
      complete installation).
    </para>
    <para>
      For the signature-handling, please read the <emphasis>Software</emphasis> chapter
      of this documentation.
    </para>
      </note>
    </section>
  <section id="CreateProfile.Reporting">
    <title id="CreateProfile.Reporting.title">
      Reporting
    </title>     

    <para>
      The <emphasis>report</emphasis> resource manages 3 types of pop-ups
      that may appear during installation.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Messages Popups (Usually non-critical, informative messages)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Warning Popups (If something might go wrong)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Error Popups (In the case of an error)
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <example>
      <title>Reporting Behavior</title>
      <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.reporting.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>	  
	</screen>
      </example>    

  <para>
    Depending on your experience, you can skip, log and show (with timeout)
    those messages. It is recommended to show all
    <emphasis>messages</emphasis> with timeout. Warnings can be skipped in
    some places but should not be ignored.
  </para>
  <para>
    By default, the settings in auto-installation mode is to show all messages without logging and
    with a timeout of 10 seconds.
  </para>
    <warning>
      <title>
	Critical system messages
      </title>
      <para>
	Note that <emphasis>not</emphasis> all messages during installation are controlled by the
	<emphasis>report</emphasis> resource. Some critical messages concerning
	package installation and partitioning will still show up ignoring your
	settings in the <emphasis>report</emphasis> section. Mostly those
	messages will have to be answered with <emphasis>Yes</emphasis> or <emphasis>No</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </warning>    
  </section>




  <section id="CreateProfile.Bootloader">
    <title>The Boot loader</title>
    <para>
      It is now possible to specify which bootloader needs to be
      installed and it  is possible to specify sections and
      more bootloader options.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the bootloader resource is not configured at all, the system will
      propose a configuration based on the partitioning scheme. If no global
      variables are configured, the system will propose a configuration for the
      global variables based on the partitioning scheme. Similarly, if no
      sections are configured, the system will propose a section configuration.
      No changes or additions will be made to existing global variables or
      existing sections.
    </para>
    <para>
      In some cases you must  decide  where to install the bootloader (the
      Master Boot Record or the first sector of the <filename>/boot</filename>
      partition) and must specify additional options for the bootloader to be
      installed correctly.
    </para>
    <note>
      <title>Boot Partition on IA64 Systems</title>
      <para>
	The boot partition on <emphasis>IA64</emphasis> is
	<emphasis>/boot/efi</emphasis> and is set to this value if only
	<emphasis>/boot</emphasis> is configured in the control
	file.
      </para>
    </note>  
    <para>
      Additionally, you can configure  special kernel and boot parameters, Kernel
      parameters can be configured using the <emphasis>kernel_parameters</emphasis> property. 
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Bootloader configuration</title>
      <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.bootloader.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	</screen>
      </example>
  
  <para>
    The <emphasis>global</emphasis> resource is used to configure additional
    boot loader options. Note that bootloaders can have different configurable
    options. Consult the documentation for the specific bootloader you want to
    use before adding any options.
  </para>
  <para>
    For example, to configure the serial console with
    <emphasis>grub</emphasis>, you can add the following options:
  </para>
    <example>
      <title>Serial console configuration with GRUB</title>
      <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.bootloader1.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	</screen>
      </example>
  
  <tip>
    <para>
      The bootloader configuration interface offers more
      configuration options than one might need for a regular setup. The
      options described in the example above should be sufficient for most
      cases.
    </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
    In the current version, bootloader configuration also supports different
    architectures and boards. The configuration of the bootloader can be done
    offline using &autoyast;. For example, the bootloader configuration for 
    PPC has the following additional options:
    
  </para>
    <example>
      <title>Bootloader configuration for PPC</title>
      <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.bootloader2.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	</screen>
      </example>
  <para>Currently the following bootloaders can be configured offline using the
  &autoyast; interface:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>LILO</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>GRUB</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>ELILO</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>zipl</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>yaboot</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  </section>

  <section id="CreateProfile.Partitioning">
    <title>
      Partitioning
    </title>

    <section>
        <title>drive configuration</title>
          <para>
          The following elements must be between the &lt;partitioning config:type="list"&gt;&lt;drive&gt; ... &lt;/drive&gt;&lt;/partitioning&gt; tags in the &lt;profile&gt; section.
          </para>
          <table frame='top'>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Attribute</entry>
                <entry>Values</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>device</entry>
                <entry>the device you want to configure in this section. Since SUSE Linux 10.1 and SLES10, you can use persistent device names via id, like <emphasis>/dev/disk/by-id/edd-int13_dev80</emphasis>. With SLES10 SP1 and SUSE Linux 10.2, <emphasis>by-path</emphasis> is possible too like <emphasis>/dev/disk/by-path/pci-0001:00:03.0-scsi-0:0:0:0</emphasis>.
                  <para><screen>&lt;device&gt;/dev/hda&lt;/device&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>optional. If left out, autoyast tries to guess the device. A RAID must always have "/dev/md" as device</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>initialize</entry>
                <entry>if set to true, the partition table gets wiped out before autoyast starts the partition calculation
<para><screen>&lt;initialize config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/initialize&gt;</screen></para>
</entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is false.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>is_lvm_vg</entry>
                <entry>This tells autoyast that this device is not a physical device but a LVM volume group (see LVM configuration below)
<para><screen>&lt;is_lvm_vg config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/is_lvm_vg&gt;</screen></para>
</entry>
                <entry>DEPRECATED since SLES10SP1 and SL10.2 - use <emphasis>type</emphasis> instead. Must be true if this device is a LVM volume group. The default is false.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>is_evms_vg</entry>
                <entry>this tells autoyast that this device is not a physical device but an EVMS volume group (see EVMS configuration below)
<para><screen>&lt;is_evms_vg config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/is_evms_vg&gt;</screen></para>
</entry>
                <entry>DEPRECATED since SLES10SP1 and SL10.2 - use <emphasis>type</emphasis> instead. Must be true if this device is an EVMS volume group. The default is false.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>partitions</entry>
                <entry>this is a list of &lt;partition&gt; entries (see table below)
<para><screen>&lt;partitions config:type="list"&gt;&lt;partition&gt;...&lt;/partition&gt;...&lt;/partitions&gt;</screen></para>
</entry>
                <entry>optional. If no partition is specified, autoyast will create it's own idea of a nice partitioning (see Automated Partitioning below).</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>pesize</entry>
                <entry>this value makes only sense with LVM/EVMS.
<para><screen>&lt;pesize&gt;8M&lt;/pesize&gt;</screen></para>
</entry>
                <entry>optional. Default is 4M for EVMS/LVM volume groups.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>use</entry>
                <entry>this parameter tells autoyast which strategy it shall use to partition the harddisc.
<para>You can choose between:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>all (uses the whole device while calculating the new partitioning)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>linux (only existing linux partitions are used)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>free (only unused space on the device gets used. No other partitions gets touched)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>1,2,3 (a list of comma seperated numbers that indicates the partition numbers to use)</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
                <entry>this parameter should be provided</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>type</entry>
                <entry>this value describes the type of the <emphasis>drive</emphasis> and is a replacement for
<emphasis>is_lvm_vg</emphasis> and <emphasis>is_evms_vg</emphasis> used in SLES10 and SL10.1
<para>You can choose between:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>CT_DISK for physical harddisks (default)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>CT_LVM for LVM volume groups</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>CT_EVMS for EVMS volume groups</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para><screen>&lt;type config:type="symbol"&gt;CT_LVM&lt;/type&gt;</screen></para>
</entry>
                <entry>optional. Default is CT_DISK for a normal physical harddisk.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
          </table>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>partition configuration</title>
          <para>
          The following elements must be between the &lt;partitions config:type="list"&gt;&lt;partition&gt; ... &lt;/partition&gt;&lt;/partitions&gt; tags in the &lt;drive&gt; section.
          </para>
          <table frame='top'>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Attribute</entry>
                <entry>Values</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>create</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the "create" tells autoyast if this partition must be created or if it's already existing
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;create config:type="boolean"&gt;false&lt;/create&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>if set to false, there must be some information for autoyast which partition this is (like with partition_nr)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>mount</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the mountpoint of this partition.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;mount&gt;/&lt;/mount&gt;</screen></para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;mount&gt;swap&lt;/mount&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>you should have at least a root partition (/) and a swap partition</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>fstopt</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    mount options for this partition
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;fstopt&gt;ro,noatime,user,data=ordered,acl,user_xattr&lt;/fstopt&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>see "man mount" for the mountoptions you can use</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>label</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the label the partition has (useful for the "mountby" parameter - see below).
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;label&gt;mydata&lt;/label&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>see "man e2label" for example.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>uuid</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the uuid the partition has (only useful for the "mountby" parameter - see below).
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;uuid&gt;1b4e28ba-2fa1-11d2-883f-b9a761bde3fb&lt;/uuid&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>see "man uuidgen"</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>size</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the size for the partition like 4G, 4500M, ... The /boot partition and the swap partition can have "auto" as
                    size too, to let autoyast calculate a reasonable size for them. On partition can have the value "max" to fillup
                    all available space.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    with SUSE Linux 10.2 and SLES10 SP1, you can specify the the size in percentage. So 10% will use 10% of the size
                    of the harddisk/VG. You can mix auto,max,sizes and percentage like you want.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;size&gt;10G&lt;/size&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>format</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    shall autoyast format the partition?
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;format config:type="boolean"&gt;false&lt;/format&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>if "create" is true, then it's very likely that this is true too</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>filesystem</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    what filesystem is used on this partition?
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>reiser (the default)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>ext2</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>ext3</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>xfs</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>jfs</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;filesystem config:type="symbol"&gt;reiser&lt;/filesystem&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is reiser</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>partition_nr</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the partition_nr this partition has/will have. If you have set create=false, then you can tell
                    autoyast which partition you mean by the partition_nr. You can force autoyast to create only
                    primary partitions by configuring only partition numbers below 5.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;partition_nr config:type="integer"&gt;2&lt;/partition_nr&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>in most cases nr. 1-4 are primary partitions and 5-... are logical partitions</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>partition_id</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                        the partition_id configures the id of the partition. If you want something else than 131
                        for linux partition or 130 for swap, you must configure that with partition_id.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;partition_id config:type="integer"&gt;131&lt;/partition_id&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>the default is 131 for linux partition. 130 for swap is set by autoyast itself too.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>filesystem_id</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                        look at partition_id above. For historical reasons they represent the same.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;filesystem_id config:type="integer"&gt;131&lt;/filesystem_id&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>since 10.1 and SLES10 it's recommended to use partition_id instead.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>mountby</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    instead of a partition number, you can tell autoyast to mount a partition by label or by uuid
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;mountby config:type="symbol"&gt;label&lt;/mountby&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>see "label" and "uuid" documentation above</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>lv_name</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    if this partition is in a logical volume in a volume group (LVM or EVMS)
                    (see is_lvm_vg/is_evms_vg parameter in drive configuration) you
                    must specifiy the logical volume name here.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;lv_name&gt;opt_lv&lt;/lv_name&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>lvm_group</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    if this is a physical partition that is used by (part of) a volume group (LVM), 
                        you have to specify the name of the volume
                    group here.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;lvm_group&gt;system&lt;/lvm_group&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>evms_group</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    if this physical partition is used by a volume group (EVMS), you have to specify the name of the volume
                    group here.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;evms_group&gt;system&lt;/evms_group&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>raid_name</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    this physical volume is part of a RAID and the name of the raid is specified here.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;raid_name&gt;/dev/md0&lt;/raid_name&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>raid_type</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    this physical volume is part of a RAID and the type of the raid is specified here..
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;raid_type&gt;raid1&lt;/raid_type&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>raid_options</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    special options for the raid are specified here. See below.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;raid_options&gt;...&lt;/raid_options&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>resize</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    This parameter is available since SLES10 SP1 and OpenSUSE 10.2.
                    This boolean must be true if an existing partition should be resized. In this case,
                    you want to set <emphasis>create</emphasis> to <emphasis>false</emphasis> too and in
                    most cases you don't want to <emphasis>format</emphasis> the partition. You need to
                    tell autoyast the <emphasis>partition_nr</emphasis> and the <emphasis>size</emphasis>.
                    The size can be in percentage of the original size or as a number of the new size, like
                    <emphasis>800M</emphasis>. <emphasis>max</emphasis> and <emphasis>auto</emphasis> don't
                    work as size here.
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;resize config:type="boolean"&gt;false&lt;/resize&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>The resize only works with physical disks. Not with LVM/EVMS volumes.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
          </table>
        </section>
    <section>
        <title>raid options</title>
          <para>
          The following elements must be between the &lt;partition&gt;&lt;raid_options&gt; ... &lt;/raid_options&gt;&lt;/partition&gt; tags.
          </para>
          <table frame='top'>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Attribute</entry>
                <entry>Values</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>chunk_size</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;chunk_size&gt;4&lt;/chunk_size&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>parity_algorithm</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    possible values are: left_asymmetric, left_symmetric, right_asymmetric, right_symmetric
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;parity_algorithm&gt;left_asymmetric&lt;/parity_algorithm&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>raid_type</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    possible values are raid0,raid1 and raid5
                  </para>
                  <para><screen>&lt;raid_type&gt;raid1&lt;/raid_type&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>the default is raid1</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
         </table>
        </section>
    <section>
      <title>
	Automated Partitioning
      </title>

      <para>
	For the automated partitioning to be completed, only the sizes and mount points of
	partitions can be provided. All other data needed for successful partitioning
	can be calculated during installation if they were not provided in the control file. 
      </para>
      <para>
	If no partitions are defined and the specified drive is also the drive where
	the root partition should be created, the following partitions are created
	automatically:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>/boot</emphasis>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Size of the <emphasis>/boot</emphasis> is determined by the
	    architecture of the target system.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>swap</emphasis>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Size of the <emphasis>swap</emphasis> partitions is determined by the
	    amount of memory available in the system.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>/</emphasis> (root partition)
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Size of the <emphasis>/</emphasis> (root partition) is the space left
	    after creating <emphasis>swap</emphasis> and <emphasis>/boot</emphasis>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>
	Depending on the initial status of the drive and how it was
	previously partitioned, it is possible to create the <emphasis>default</emphasis>
	partitioning in the following ways:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Use free space</emphasis>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    If the drive is already partitioned, it is possible to create the
	    new partitions using the available space on the hard drive. This
	    requires the availability of enough space for all selected
	    packages in addition to swap.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Reuse all available space</emphasis>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This option will lead to the deletion of all existing
	    partitions (Linux and non-Linux partitions).

	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Reuse all available Linux partitions</emphasis>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This option will lead to the deletion of existing Linux
	    partitions. All other partitions (i.e. Windows) will be
	    kept. Note that this works only if the Linux partitions are at the end of the device.
	    
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Reuse only specified partitions</emphasis>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This option will lead to the deletion of the specified partitions.
	    The selection of the partitions scheduled for deletion should be
	    started from the last available partition.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	Repartitioning using only some of the existing partitions can be
	accomplished only if the region selected to be partitioned exists at
	the end of the device and only with neighboring partitions. This
	means that you cannot repartition a region which contains a partition that
	should not be touched in the middle.
      </para>

      <caution>
	<title>Important Notice</title>
	<para>
	  The value provided in the <emphasis>use</emphasis> property determines how existing data and
	  partitions are treated. The value <emphasis>all</emphasis> means that
	  <emphasis>ALL</emphasis> data on the disk will
	  be erased. Make backups and use the <emphasis>confirm</emphasis>
	  property if you are going to
	  keep some partitions with important data. This is automated
	  installation and no pop-ups will  notify you about partitions being deleted.
	</para>
      </caution>
      <para>	
	In case of the presence of multiple drives in the target system, all
	drives must be identified with their device names and how the partitioning should be performed.
      </para>

      <para>
	Partition sizes can be given in Gigabytes, Megabytes or can be set to
	a flexible value using the keywords <emphasis>auto</emphasis> and
	<emphasis>max</emphasis>. <emphasis>max</emphasis> is used to fill a
	partition to the maximal available space on a
	drive (Which mean that the partition should be the last one on the drive). 
	<emphasis>auto</emphasis> can be used to determine the size of
	a <emphasis>swap</emphasis> or <emphasis>boot</emphasis> partitions
	depending on the memory available and the type of the system.
      </para>
      <para>A fixed size can be given as shown below:</para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>1GB</emphasis> will create a partition with 1 GB size.
	<emphasis>1500MB</emphasis> will create a partition which is 1.5 GB big.
      </para>
      <example>
	<title>Automated partitioning</title>
	<para>
	  The following is an example of a single drive system, which is not
	  pre-partitioned and should be automatically partitioned according to
	  the described pre-defined partition plan. If you leave the device out,
      an autodetection of the device will happen. So you don't have to do
      different profiles for /dev/sda or /dev/hda systems.
	</para>
	<screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.partitioning.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  
	  </screen>
	</example>
  <para>
    A more detailed example shows how existing partitions  and
    multiple drives are handled.
  </para>
  <example>
    <title>Detailed automated partitioning</title>
    <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.partitioning2.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      	  </screen>
	</example>
    </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advanced Partitioning features</title>
    <section>
      <title>Wipe out partition table</title>
      <para>
        In the most cases this is not needed because autoyast can delete partitions
        one by one automatically but you have the option to let autoyast clear the partition table
        instead of deleting the partitions individually.
      </para>
      <para>
        if you go into the "drive" section, you can add
        <screen>
<![CDATA[
<initialize config:type="boolean">true</initialize>
]]>
</screen>
        which tells Autoyast to delete the partition table before it starts to analyse the
        actual partitioning and calculates it's partition plan. Of course this means, that you
        can't keep any of your existing partitions.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Mount Options</title>
      <para>
	By default a file system which is to be mounted is
	identified in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> by the device name. This identification
	can be changed so the file system  is found by searching
	for a <acronym>UUID</acronym> or a volume label. Note that not all file systems can be mounted
	by <acronym>UUID</acronym> or a volume label. To specify how a
	partition is to be mounted, use the <emphasis>mountby</emphasis>
	property which has the <emphasis>symbol</emphasis> type. Possible
	options are:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>device (default)</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>label</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>UUID</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	If you choose to mount the partition using a label, the name
	entered in the <emphasis>label</emphasis> property is used as the
	volume label. 
      </para>
      <para>
	Add any legal mount option allowed in the fourth field of
	<filename>/etc/fstab</filename>. Multiple options are separated by commas.  Possible fstab options:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>Mount Read-Only (ro):</emphasis> No writable
	    access to the file system is possible. Default is false.</para>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>No access time (noatime):</emphasis> Access times
	    are not updated when a file is read. Default is false.</para>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>Mountable by User (user):</emphasis> The file
	    system may be mounted by an ordinary user. Default is
	    false.</para>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Data Journaling Mode (ordered | journal |
	      writeback) :</emphasis> Specifies the journaling mode for
	    file data. journal -- All data is committed into the journal
	    prior to being written into the main file system. ordered --
	    All data is forced directly out to the main file system prior
	    to its meta data being committed to the journal. writeback --
	    Data ordering is not preserved.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Access Control List (acl):</emphasis> Enable access
	    control lists on the file system.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Extended User Attributes (user_xattr):</emphasis> Allow
	    extended user attributes on the file system.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	
      </itemizedlist>
      <example>
	<title>Mount Options</title>

	<screen>
	    <xi:include href="examples/example.mountoptions.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  
	</screen>
      </example>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Creating Primary and Extended Partitions</title>
      <para>
	By default, &autoyast2; will create an extended partition and will add all
	other new partitions as logical devices. It is possible however to
	instruct &autoyast2; to create a certain partition as a primary
	or as extended partition. Additionally, it is possible to
	specify the size of a partition using sectors instead of the size in Mbytes.
      </para>
      <para>
	The properties <emphasis>partition_id</emphasis> and
	<emphasis>partition_type</emphasis> control such behavior. To
	specify the size in sectors, the list resource
	<emphasis>region</emphasis> can be used.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Advanced Automated partitioning</title>
      <screen>
	    <xi:include href="examples/example.advancedPartitioning.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </screen>
    </example>
  
      <para>
	The last example  only makes sense if you exactly know the
	boundaries of the partitions and it does only make sense if you are creating
	an exact copy of  a system, for example when cloning. The first
	region entry in the list is the beginning of the region, the second
	represents the length of the region.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The following example lets you create an extended partition with a
	custom size.
      </para>
	  <example>
	    <title>
	      Creating custom extended partitions
	    </title>	   	    
	    <screen>
      	    <xi:include href="examples/example.customextended.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </screen>
  </example>


    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Keeping Specific Partitions</title>
      <para>
	In some cases you might choose to keep some partitions untouched
	and only format specific target partitions, rather than creating them from
	scratch. This might be the case of Linux installations have to
	co-exist with another operating system or if certain partitions
	contain data that you wish to keep untouched.
      </para>
      <para>
	Such scenarios require certain knowledge about the target systems
	and hard drives. Depending on the scenario, you might need to know
	the exact partition table of the target hard drive with partition
	id's, sizes and numbers. With such data you can tell &autoyast; to
	keep certain partitions, format others and create new partitions if 
	needed.
      </para>

      <para>
	The following example will keep partitions 1, 2 and 5 and delete
	partition 6 to create two new partitions. All kept partitions will
	be only formatted.
      </para>
    <example>
      <title>
	Keeping partitions
      </title>	   	    
      <screen>
	    <xi:include href="examples/example.keepingpart.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </screen>
    </example>
    <para>
	The last example requires exact knowledge about the existing partition
	table and about the partition numbers of those partitions that
	should be kept. In some cases however, such data might be not
	available, especially in a mixed hardware environment with
	different hard drive types and configurations. The following
	scenario is for a system with a non-Linux OS with a designated
	area for a Linux installation.     
      </para>
      <figure id="partitioning-keep1">
	<title id="partitioning-keep1.title" >Keeping partitions</title>
	<mediaobject>&partitioning-keep1;</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
	In this scenario and as shown in  figure <quote><link
	    linkend='partitioning-keep1'
	    endterm="partitioning-keep1.title"/></quote> , &autoyast2;
	should not in any case create any new
	partitions,  instead  it should search for certain partition types on the system and use
	them according to the partitioning plan in the control file. No
	partition numbers are given in this case, only the mount points and
	the partition types (Additional configuration data can be provided,
	for example file system options, encryption and filesystem type)
      </para>
  <example>
    <title> Auto-detection of partitions to be kept.</title>
    <screen>   <xi:include href="examples/example.autodetectpart.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></screen>
  </example>
    </section>	
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using existing mount table (fstab)</title>
    <note>
      <title>New Feature</title>
    </note>
    <para>
      This option will allow the AutoYaST to use an existing
      <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> and use the partition data from
      from a previous installation. All partitions are kept and no new
      partitions are created. The found partitions will be formatted and
      mounted as specified in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> found on a
      Linux root partition.
    </para>
    <para>
      Although the default behaviour is to format all partitions, it is
      also possible to leave some partitions untouched and only mount them,
      for example data partitions. If multiple installations are found on
      the system (multiple root partitions with different
      <emphasis>fstab</emphasis> files, the installation will abort, unless
      the desired root partition is configured in the control file. The
      following example illustrates how this option can be used:
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>
	Reading existing <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>
      </title>
      <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.fstab.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </screen>
	</example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>
      Logical Volume Manager (LVM)
    </title>
    <para>
      To configure LVM, first you need to create a <emphasis>physical volume</emphasis> using the
      normal partitioning method described above. 
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>
	Create LVM Physical Volume
      </title>
      <para>
	The following example shows how to prepare for LVM in the
	<emphasis>partitioning</emphasis> resource:
      </para>
      <screen>
 <xi:include href="examples/example.lvmvolume.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </screen>

    </example>
    <para>
      The last example will create a non-formatted partition on device
      <filename>/dev/sda1</filename> of the type <emphasis>LVM</emphasis> and
      with the volume group <emphasis>system</emphasis>. The partition
      created  will use all available space on this drive.
    </para>

	<example>
	  <title>
	    LVM Logical Volumes (New syntax)
	  </title>
	  <screen>
<xi:include href="examples/example.lvmnew.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	  </screen>
	</example>
    <para>
      With SUSE Linux 10.1 and all following versions, it's possible to set the <emphasis>size</emphasis> 
      to <emphasis>max</emphasis> for the logical volumes. Of course, you can only use <emphasis>max</emphasis>
      only for one(!) logical volumes. You can't have two logical volumes in one volume group with the 
      <emphasis>size</emphasis> set to <emphasis>max</emphasis>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>
      Enterprise Volume Management System (EVMS)
    </title>
    <para>
      Since SLES10 autoyast has EVMS support.
    </para>
    <para>
      Using EVMS is quite similar to using LVM (see above). So switching from LVM to EVMS
      is just a small change in the autoyast profile. All you have to do is to change the
      "is_lvm_vg" element into "is_evms_vg" and the "lvm_group" element into "evms_group".
    </para>
    <para>
      With autoyast it's not possible to mix LVM and EVMS.
    </para>
    <para>
      Using the LVM example from above for EVMS now looks like this:
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>
        EVMS Logical Volumes
      </title>
      <screen>
<xi:include href="examples/example.evms.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </screen>
    </example>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Software RAID</title>
    <para>
      Using &autoyast;, you can create and assemble software RAID devices. The
      supported RAID levels are the following:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>	  
	<para>
	  <emphasis>RAID 0:</emphasis> This level increases your disk performance.
	  There is <emphasis>NO</emphasis> redundancy in this mode. If one
	  of the drives crashes, data recovery will not be possible.

	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>RAID 1:</emphasis>This mode has the best redundancy. It can be
	  used with two or more disks. This mode maintains an exact copy of all data on all
	  disks. As long as at least one disk is still working, no data is lost. The partitions
	  used for this type of RAID should have approximately the same size.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>RAID 5:</emphasis> This mode combines management of a larger number
	  of disks and still maintains some redundancy. This mode can be used on three disks or more.
	  If one disk fails, all data is still intact. If two disks fail simultaneously,
	  all data is lost.
	</para>	  
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Multipath:</emphasis>This mode allow access to the same physical device
	  over multiple controller for redundancy against a fault in a controller
	  card. This mode can be used with at least two devices.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      As with LVM, you need to create all <emphasis><acronym>RAID</acronym></emphasis> partitions first and assign
      the partitions to the <acronym>RAID</acronym> device you want to
      create and additionally you need to  specify whether a partition or a device should be configured in the
      <acronym>RAID</acronym>  or if it should configured as a <emphasis>Spare</emphasis> device.
    </para>
    <para>
      The following example shows a simple RAID1 configuration:
    </para>
  

  	<example>
	  <title>RAID1 configuration</title>
      <screen>
<xi:include href="examples/example.raidnew.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	    </screen>
	  </example>


    <para>
      The following has to be taken into consideration when configuring
      raid:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>The device for raid is always <emphasis>/dev/md</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The property <emphasis>partition_nr</emphasis> is used to
	  determine the MD device number. if
	  <emphasis>partition_nr</emphasis> is equal to 0, then
	  <emphasis>/dev/md0</emphasis> is configured.</para>	   
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>All RAID specific options are contained in the
	  <emphasis>raid_options</emphasis> resource.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>



  </section>
  </section>      
  <section id="CreateProfile.Software">
    <title>
      Software
    </title>
    
    <section id="Software.Selections">
      <title>
	Package Selections until SUSE Linux 10.1 (not SLES10)
      </title>
      <para>	
	You can install software on the new system using a pre-defined package base selection, i.e. Minimal, Minimal+X11,
	default etc. in addition to several <emphasis>Add-on</emphasis> selections. 
	Check the first CD for available selections in
	<filename>suse/setup/descr/selections</filename>, depending on the
	product you are installing, some "well-known" selections might not
	be available.
      </para>
      
      
      <para>
	In the control file, packages and package selections are described as
	the following:
      </para>
	<example>
	  <title>
	    Package selection in control file
	  </title>
	  <screen>
<xi:include href="examples/example.software.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	  </screen>
	</example>     
      <para>
	You can install one base selection and additionally one or multiple 
	add-on selections.
      </para>
      <para>
	When installing from a CD-ROM, needed packages from other CD-ROMs
	are installed after the initial boot of the
	system in the second installation phase. If you
	are installing packages from multiple CD-ROMs, then
	auto-installation has to be interrupted for switching the
	CD-ROMs. In the case of NFS installation, all packages are
	installed at first stage of the installation only if the NFS repository
	is configured as a single medium.
      </para>
      <para>
	It is often required, that a package should be installed in the
	second phase, especially custom packages
	which may contain scripts for configuring the system. This can be
	done using the <emphasis>post-packages</emphasis> resource.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="Software.Selections.sles10">
      <title>
	Package Selections with patterns (SLES10 and SUSE Linux 10.2)
      </title>
      <para>
      SLES10 no longer supports <emphasis>selections</emphasis> but uses 
      <emphasis>patterns</emphasis> now. Autoyast is not be able to convert 
      selections into patterns and so you have to do that on your own.
      If you want to use a SLES9 autoyast profile to install a SLES10
      server, you have to remove all <emphasis>addon</emphasis> entries and the
      <emphasis>base</emphasis> entry. Patterns are configured like this:
      </para>
	<example>
	  <title>
	    Package selection in control file with patterns
	  </title>
	  <screen>
<xi:include href="examples/example.software.patterns.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	  </screen>
	</example>
    <para>
      As you can see, the <emphasis>packages</emphasis> section is still the same like on
      a SLES9. Just the <emphasis>addon</emphasis> and <emphasis>base</emphasis> is gone.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>
	Custom Package Selections
      </title>
      <para>	
	In addition to the pre-defined selections, you can create custom selections
	by providing  a selection file in the selection
	directory. (<filename>suse/setup/descr</filename>) The selection files have a special format and any
	additional selection file must conform to this format, otherwise
	&yast2; will not be able to read it.	  	  
      </para>
      <para>
	As an example for the selection file, take a look at the files
	available in the directory <filename>/suse/setup/descr/</filename> on
	the CD-ROMs.
      </para>
      <para>
	After creating a selection file, you can add it to the configuration
	as described earlier in this section. The selection name, for example
      <emphasis>My.sel</emphasis> has to be added to the index files
      <filename>selections</filename> and <filename>directory.yast</filename>
      to make it visible to the installer.
    </para>
    <para>
      The file <filename>My.sel</filename> should have the following format:
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>
	Customized Package selection
	</title>
	<screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.customSoftware3.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
         </screen>
        </example>
  <para>To use the above selection, the following should be added in the
    control file:</para>
  <example>
    <title>
      Package selection file
    </title>
    <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.customSoftware.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
          </screen>
        </example>

      </section>
  <section>
    <title>
      Installing additional and customized Packages
    </title>
    <para>
      In addition to the packages available for installation on the CD-ROMs,
      you can add external  packages including customized  kernels. Customized
      kernel packages must be compatible to the  &company-suse;  packages and must
      install the kernel files to the same locations.
    </para>
    <para>
      Unlike earlier versions, to install custom and external packages
      there is no need for a special resource in the control
      file. Instead you need to re-create the package database and update
      it with any new packages or new package versions in the source repository.
    </para>
    <para>
      A script is provided for this task which will query packages
      available in the repository and create the required package
      database.
    </para>    
      
    <para>
      Creating a new package database is only needed if new RPMs
      (i.e. update RPMs) were added. To re-create the database, use the
      <command>/usr/bin/create_package_descr</command>
      command. For example, use this command line to create the package
      database. (When creating the database, all languages will be reset to English).
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Creating package database</title>
      <screen>
	cd /usr/local/CDs/LATEST/suse
	create_package_descr  -x PATH_TO_EXTRA_PROV -d /usr/local/CDs/LATEST/suse 
      </screen>
    </example>
    <note>
      <title>Change starting from SUSE Linux 9.1/SLES 9</title>
      <para>To provide extra dependencies which can not be extracted from the
	rpm files, an extra file with missing dependencies is available in the
	directory <filename>suse/setup/descr</filename>. The file
	<filename>EXTRA_PROV</filename> can be used when recreating the package
	database using the <emphasis>-x</emphasis> option.</para>
    </note>
    <para>
      In the above example, the directory
      <filename>/usr/local/CDs/LATEST/suse</filename> contains the architecture
      dependent and independent packages, i.e. <emphasis>noarch</emphasis> and <emphasis>i586</emphasis>. 
      This might look different on other architectures.
    </para>
    <para>
      The advantage of this method is that you can keep an up-to-date
      repository with fixed and updated package (i.e. from &company-suse; FTP
      server). Additionally this method  makes the creation of custom CD-ROMs easier.
    </para>
    <note>
        <title>Change starting from SUSE Linux 10.1/SLES 10</title>
        <para>
        With SLES10/SL10.1, the concept of adding own RPMs to an installation source has changed.
        The <emphasis>yast/order</emphasis> and <emphasis>yast/instorder</emphasis> is no longer supported. Neither
        by AutoYaST nor by YaST. To add own RPMs to an installation source (that includes add-on products like the
        SDK) you have to add a file <emphasis>add_on_products</emphasis> to the CD1 of the main product.
        <screen>
media_url [path_on_media [product_1 [product_2 [....]]]
        </screen>
        media_url is URL of the media itself
        path_on_media is path of the catalog on the media. If not present, / (root) is assumed
        product_1 and following are the names for products, which should be marked for installation. If no product is mentioned, all products found on the media are selected for installation.
        For example:
        <screen>
http://192.168.66.6/SLES10/sdk/CD1
http://192.168.66.6/SLES10/CD1/updates
        </screen>
        Besides that <emphasis>add_on_products</emphasis> file, you can use the autoyast profile to specify add-on products. For example:
        <screen>
&lt;add-on&gt;
 &lt;add_on_products config:type=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
   &lt;listentry&gt;
     &lt;media_url&gt;http://192.168.66.6/SLES10/CD1/updates&lt;/media_url&gt;
     &lt;product&gt;SuSE-Linux-Updates&lt;/product&gt;
     &lt;product_dir&gt;/&lt;/product_dir&gt;
   &lt;/listentry&gt;
 &lt;/add_on_products&gt;
&lt;/add-on&gt;
        </screen>
        With that entry in the autoyast profile, the <emphasis>add_on_products</emphasis> file is not necessary.
        </para>
        <para>
        YaST checks the signatures of files on the installation source now. If a <emphasis>content</emphasis> file is
        not signed, during a manual installation YaST asks the user what to do. During an autoinstallation, the
        installation source gets rejected silently.
        </para>
    </note>
    <para>
        If you want to use unsigned installation sources with autoyast, you can turn of the checks with the following
        configuration in your autoyast profile (part of the <emphasis>general</emphasis> section.
    </para>
          <para>
          The following elements must be between the &lt;general&gt;&lt;signature-handling&gt; ... &lt;/signature-handling&gt;&lt;/general&gt; tags.
          </para>
    <para>
          <table frame='top'>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Attribute</entry>
                <entry>Values</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>accept_unsigned_file</entry>
                <entry>the installer will accept unsigned files like the content file
                  <para><screen>&lt;accept_unsigned_file config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/accept_unsigned_file&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>optional. If left out, autoyast lets yast decide what to do</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>accept_file_without_checksum</entry>
                <entry>the installer will accept files without a checksum in the content file
                  <para><screen>&lt;accept_file_without_checksum config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/accept_file_without_checksum&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>optional. If left out, autoyast lets yast decide what to do</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>accept_verification_failed</entry>
                <entry>the installer will accept files where the verification of the signature failed. So the file was signed but the check failed.
                  <para><screen>&lt;accept_verification_failed config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/accept_verification_failed&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>optional. If left out, autoyast lets yast decide what to do</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>accept_unknown_gpg_key</entry>
                <entry>the installer will accept new gpg keys on the installation source that are used to sign the content file for example
                  <para><screen>&lt;accept_unknown_gpg_key config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/accept_unknown_gpg_key&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>optional. If left out, autoyast lets yast decide what to do</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>accept_non_trusted_gpg_key</entry>
                <entry>This basically means, we know the key, but it is not trusted
                  <para><screen>&lt;accept_non_trusted_gpg_key config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/accept_non_trusted_gpg_key&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>optional. If left out, autoyast lets yast decide what to do</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>import_gpg_key</entry>
                <entry>the installer will accept and import new gpg keys on the installation source in it's database.
                  <para><screen>&lt;import_gpg_key config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/import_gpg_key&gt;</screen></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>optional. If left out, autoyast lets yast decide what to do</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Kernel packages</title>
    <para>
      Kernel packages are not part of any selection. The required kernel
      is determined during installation. If the kernel package is added to any selection
      or to the individual package selection, installation will mostly fail due to conflicts.
    </para>
    <para>
      To force the installation of a specific kernel, use the
      <emphasis>kernel</emphasis> property. The following is an example
      forcing the installation of the default kernel. In this example this
      kernel will be installed in any case, even if an SMP or other kernel
      is required</para>
   	<example>
	  <title>
	    Package selection in control file
	  </title>
	  <screen>
<xi:include href="examples/example.kernel.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

	  </screen>
	</example>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Removing automatically selected packages</title>
    <para>
      Some packages are selected automatically either because of a
      dependency or because it available in a selection.
    </para>
    <para>
      Removing such packages might break the system consistency and it is
      not recommended to remove basic packages unless a replacement which
      provides same services is provided. Best example for this case are
      <acronym>MTA</acronym> packages. By default, <emphasis>postfix</emphasis>
      will be selected and installed. If you wish however to use another
      <acronym>MTA</acronym> like <emphasis>sendmail</emphasis>, then
      postfix can be removed from the list of selected package using a list
      in the software resource. The following example shows how this can be done:
      
    </para>
	<example>
	  <title>
	    Package selection in control file
	  </title>
	  <screen>
<xi:include href="examples/example.removesoft.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>


	  </screen>
	</example>   
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Installing packages during stage 2</title>
    <para>
      if you want to install packages after the reboot during stage 2, instead of
      during the normal installation process in stage 1, you can use the
      <emphasis>post-packages</emphasis> element for that:
    </para>
        <screen>
&lt;software&gt;
  &lt;post-packages config:type=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
    &lt;package&gt;yast2-cim&lt;/package&gt;
  &lt;/post-packages&gt;
&lt;/software&gt;
        </screen>
  </section>
    </section>

  <section id="CreateProfile.Services">
    <title>
      Services and Run-levels
    </title>
    <para>
      With the run-level resource you can set the default run-level and specify
      in detail which system services you want to be started in which
      run-level.
    </para>
    <para>
      The default property specifies the <emphasis>default</emphasis> run
      level of the system. Changes to the default run-level will take effect
      the next time you boot the system. After installation is completed,
      the system has run-level 5, which is  <emphasis>Full multiuser with
	network and XDM</emphasis>. If you have configured a system with no
      X11, then it is recommended to reboot the system after the first stage
      using the <emphasis>reboot</emphasis> property in the <emphasis>general</emphasis> resource.

    </para>
    <para>
      A service should run in using a space delimited list of the run-levels
      as shown in the  following example. An alternative to specifying the
      exact run-levels is to change the status of the service by either
      enabling or disabling it using the
      <emphasis>service_status</emphasis> property.
    </para>
    &example.runlevels;
    
  </section>

  <section id="CreateProfile.Network">
    <title>
      Network configuration
    </title>

    <section id="Configuration.Network.Devices">
      <title>
	Network devices, DNS and Routing.
      </title>
      <para>
	Network configuration is used to connect a single  &company-suse;  Linux
	workstation to an Ethernet-based LAN or to configure dial-up
	connection. More complex configuration (multiple network cards,
	routing, etc.) is also provided. With this module it's possible to
	configure and setup Ethernet Controllers and Token-Ring Controllers.
      </para>
      <para>
	To configure network settings and activate networking automatically,
	one global resource is used to store the whole network configuration.
      </para>
      
      &example.network;
    </section>

    <section id="Configuration.Network.Proxy">
      <title>
	Proxy
      </title>
      <para>
	Configure your Internet proxy (caching) settings using this
	resource.
      </para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>HTTP proxy</emphasis> is the name of the proxy server for your access to the world wide web (WWW).
	<emphasis>FTP proxy</emphasis> is the name of the proxy server for your access to the file transfer services (FTP).
	<emphasis>No proxy</emphasis> domains is a list of domains for
	which the requests should be done directly without caching.
      </para>
      <para>
	If you are using a proxy server with authorization, fill in Proxy user name and Proxy password.
      </para>
      <example>
	<title>
	  Netwrok configuration: Proxy
	</title>
	<screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.proxy.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>	  
	  </screen>
	</example>

      
    </section>
    <section id="Configuration.Network.Inetd">
      <title>(X)Inetd </title>

      <para>
	The profile has elements to specify which superserver should be
	used (netd_service), whether it should be enabled (netd_status) and
	how the services should be configured (netd_conf).
      </para>
      <para>
	A service description element has conceptually two parts: key and
	non-key. When writing the configuration, services are matched using
	the key fields and to the matching service, non-key fields are
	applied. If no service matches, it is created. If more services
	match, a warning is reported. The key fields are script, service,
	protocol and server.
      </para>
      <para>
	Service and protocol are matched literally. script is the base name
	of the config file: usually a file in<filename> /etc/xinetd.d</filename>, for example "echo-udp",
	or "inetd.conf". For compatibility with 8.2, server is matched more
	loosely: if it is <filename>/usr/sbin/tcpd</filename>, the real server name is taken from
	server_args. After that, the basename of the first
	whitespace-sparated word is taken and these values are compared.
      </para>
      &example.inetd;

    </section>
    <section id="Configuration.Network.NIS">
      <title>NIS</title>
      <para>
	Using the <emphasis>nis</emphasis> resource, you can configure the target machine as a <emphasis>NIS
	  client</emphasis>. The following example shows a detailed
	configuration using multiple domains.
      </para>
      &example.nis;
    </section>
    <!--
    <section id="Configuration.Network.NISplus">
    <title>
    NIS+
  </title>
    <para>
    If you activate NIS+, the data of the
    NIS+ Server will be added to <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>. Keyserv and the NIS+ cache manager
    will be started and the NSS and PAM configuration will be modified to use
    NIS+ and set the Secret Key of a user.
  </para>
    &example.nisplus;
  </section>
    -->
    <section id="Configuration.Network.LDAP">
      <title>
	&ldap;  client
      </title>
      <para>
	The installed machine can be set up as an
	<emphasis>> &ldap;  client</emphasis> to authenticate  users with an
	OpenLDAP;  server. Required data are the name of the search base (base DN, e.g, dc=mydomain,dc=com)
	and the IP address of the  &ldap;  server (e.g., 10.20.0.2).
      </para>
      <para>
	If  &ldap;  is activated, <emphasis>NSS</emphasis> and <emphasis>PAM</emphasis>
	will be configured accordingly to use  &ldap;  for user authentication.
      </para>
      &example.ldapclient;
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>
	NFS Client and Server
      </title>
      <para>
	Configuration of a system as an NFS client or an NFS server is
	possible and can be done using the configuration system. The
	following example shows how both NFS client and server can be configured.
      </para>
       <example>
          <title>
            Network configuration: NFS client
          </title>
          <screen>

  <xi:include href="examples/example.nfs.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>	  
          </screen>
</example>
       <example>
          <title>
            Network configuration: NFS Server
          </title>
          <screen>

        
  <xi:include href="examples/example.nfsserver.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>	  
          </screen>
</example> 
    </section>
    
    <section id='Configuration.Network.Ntp'>
      <title>
	NTP Client
      </title>
      <para>
          Select whether to start the NTP daemon when booting the system. The NTP
          daemon resolves host names when initializing. The first
          synchronization of the clock is performed before the NTP daemon is
          started. To use this host for initial synchronization configure the
          property <emphasis>initial_sync</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
          To run NTP daemon in
          chroot jail, set <emphasis>start_in_chroot</emphasis>. Starting any daemon
          in a chroot jail is more secure and strongly recommended. 
          To adjust NTP servers, peers, local clocks, and NTP broadcasting,
          add the appropriate entry to the control file. an example of various
          configuration options is shown below.
      </para>
       <example>
          <title>
            Network configuration: NTP Client
          </title>
          <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.ntp.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>	  
          </screen>
</example> 
    </section>
  </section>
    <section id='Configuration.Network.Sendmail'>
      <title>
	Mail Configuration (Sendmail or Postfix)
      </title>
      <para>
	For the mail configuration of the client this
	module lets you create a detailed mail configuration. The module
	contains various options and it is recommended to use it at least for
	the initial configuration.
	
      </para>
       <example>
	  <title>Mail Configuration</title>
          <screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.mail.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>	  
          </screen>
</example> 
    </section>



  <section id="CreateProfile.Security">
    <title>
      Security settings
    </title>
    
    <para>
      Using the features of this module, you will be able to change the local
      security settings on the target system. The local security settings
      include the boot configuration, login settings, password settings,
      user addition settings, and file permissions.
    </para>
    <para>
      Configuring the security settings automatically corresponds to the
      <emphasis>Custom Settings</emphasis> in the security module available in
      the running system which lets you create your own, customized
      configuration.
    </para>      
    
    &example.security;
    <section>
      <title>Password Settings Options</title>
      <para>
	Change various password settings. These settings are mainly stored in the <filename>/etc/login.defs</filename> file.
      </para>
      <para>
	Use this resource to activate one of  the <emphasis>encryption</emphasis> methods currently supported.
	If not set, <emphasis>DES</emphasis> is configured.
      </para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>DES</emphasis>, the Linux default method, works in all
	network environments, but it restricts you to passwords no longer than
	eight characters. <emphasis>MD5</emphasis> allows longer passwords,
	thus provides more security, but some network protocols don't support
	this, and you may have problems with NIS. <emphasis>Blowfish</emphasis>
	is also supported.
      </para>
      <para>Additionally, you can setup the system to check for password
	plausibility and length etc.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Boot Settings</title>
      <para>
	Use the security resource, you can change various boot settings.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>How to interpret Ctrl + Alt + Del</emphasis></para>
	  <para>When someone at the console has pressed the CTRL + ALT + DEL key combination, the system usually reboots. Sometimes it is desirable to ignore this event, for example, when the system serves as both workstation and server.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>Shutdown behavior of KDM</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Set who is allowed to shut down the machine from KDM.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Login Settings</title>
      <para>Change various login settings. These settings are mainly stored in the '/etc/login.defs' file.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>New user settings (useradd settings)</title>
      <para>Set the minimum and maximum possible user ID and set the minimum
	and maximum possible group ID.
      </para>
    </section>
    
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration.X11">
    <title>
      Monitor and X11 Configuration
    </title>
    <para>
      FIXME
  </para>     

  <example>
      <title>
          X11 and Monitor configuration
      </title>
      <screen>
<xi:include href="examples/example.x11.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </screen>
  </example>
    

  </section>

  <section id="Configuration.Security.users">
    <title>
      Users
    </title>
    <para>
      The root user and at least one normal user can be added during install
      using data supplied in the control file. User data and passwords
      (encrypted or in clear text) are part of the <emphasis>configure</emphasis> resource in the
      control file.
    </para>     
    <para>
      At least the root user should be configured during
      auto-installation, which will insure you will be able to login after
      installation is finished and of course it will insure nobody else can login
      into the system (in case the password is not set).
  </para> 
  <para>The two users in the following example  are added during system
      configuration.</para>

  <example>
      <title>
          User configuration
      </title>
          <screen>
              <xi:include href="examples/example.users.xml" parse="text"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
          </screen>
      </example>
      <para>
          The last example shows the minimal information required for adding
          users. More options are available for a more customized user account
          management. The data in <filename>/etc/default/useradd</filename> is
          used to determine the home directory of the user to be created in
          addition to other parameters. 
      </para>      
  </section>
  <section id="createprofile.scripts">
    <title>Custom user scripts</title>
    <para>
      By adding scripts to the auto-installation process you can customize the
      installation for your needs and take control in different stages of the
      installation.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the auto-installation process, four types of scripts can be executed and they
      will be described here in order of "appearance" during the installation.
    </para>
    <para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><emphasis>pre-scripts</emphasis> (very early, before anything else really happened)</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>chroot-scripts</emphasis> (after the package installation, before the first boot)</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>post-scripts</emphasis> (during the first boot of the installed system, no services running)</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>init-scripts</emphasis> (during the first boot of the installed system, all servies up and running)</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <section id="pre-install.scripts">
	<title>Pre-Install Scripts</title>
	<para>
	  Executed before &yast2; does any real change to the system
	  (Before partitioning and package installation but after the hardware detection)
	</para>
    <para>
      You can use the pre-script to modify your profile and let autoyast read it again.
      If you want to do that, you can find your profile in "/tmp/profile/autoinst.xml".
      Do what you want to do with that file and store the modified version in
      "/tmp/profile/modified.xml". Autoyast will read that modified script then again after
      the pre-script is done.
    </para>
    <para>
      With SUSE Linux 10.0 and all following versions it's possible to change the partitioning with fdisk 
      in your pre-script. With pre 10.0 versions of SUSE Linux (like SLES9), that was not possible.
    </para>
	<note><title>Pre-Install Scripts with confirmation</title>
	  <para>
	    Pre-scripts are executed at an early stage of the installation.
	    This means if you have requested to confirm the installation, the 
	    pre-scripts  will be executed before the confirmation screen
	    shows up. (<emphasis>profile/install/general/mode/confirm</emphasis>)
	  </para>
	</note>
          <para>
            The following elements must be between the &lt;pre-scripts config:type="list"&gt;&lt;script&gt; ... &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/pre-scripts&gt; tags
          </para>
      <para>
        <table frame='top'>
          <title>pre script XML representation</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Element</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
                <entry>Comment</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>location</entry>
                <entry>you can define a location from where the script gets fetched.
                       Locations can be the same like for the profile (http,ftp,nfs,...).
                <para><screen>&lt;location&gt;http://10.10.0.1/myPreScript.sh&lt;/location&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>either &lt;location&gt; or &lt;source&gt; must be defined</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>source</entry>
                <entry>the script itself. The source code of the script if you want so. Encapsulated in a CDATA tag. If you don't want
                to put the whole shell script into the XML profile, look at the location parameter.

                <para><screen>&lt;source&gt;
&lt;![CDATA[ 
echo "Testing the pre script" &gt; /tmp/pre-script_out.txt 
]]&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>Either &lt;location&gt; or &lt;source&gt; must be defined</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>interpreter</entry>
                <entry>the interpreter that must be used for the script. Supported options are shell and perl.
                <para><screen>&lt;interpreter&gt;perl&lt;/interpreter&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional (default is shell)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>filename</entry>
                <entry>the filename of the script. It will be stored in a temporary directory under /tmp/...
                <para><screen>&lt;filename&gt;myPreScript5.sh&lt;/filename&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is the type of the script (pre-scripts) in this case</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>feedback</entry>
                <entry>if this boolean is true, stdout and stderr of the script will be shown in a popup that the
                       user has to confirm via ok-button. If stdout and stderr are empty, no popup is shown and so
                       no confirmation is needed.
                <para><screen>&lt;feedback config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/feedback&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is false. This option was invented with SL 10.1 / SLES10</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>debug</entry>
                <entry>if this is true, every single line of a shell script is logged. Perl scripts are run with warnings
                turned on.
                <para><screen>&lt;debug config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/debug&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is true. This option was invented with SL 10.1 / SLES10</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="chroot.scripts">
    <title>Chroot environment scripts</title>
	<para>Chroot scripts are executed before the machine reboots for the first time.
	  Actually chroot scripts are two differnt kind of script with
      one name. You can execute chroot script before the installation chroots into
      the installed system and configures the boot loader and you can execute a script
      after the chroot into the installed system has happend (look at the "chrooted" parameter for that). Both types of scripts are
      executed before yast2 boots for the first time.
	</para>
          <para>
            The following elements must be between the &lt;chroot-scripts config:type="list"&gt;&lt;script&gt; ... &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/chroot-scripts&gt; tags
          </para>
      <para>
        <table frame='top'>
          <title>chroot script XML representation</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Element</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
                <entry>Comment</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>location</entry>
                <entry>you can define a location from where the script gets fetched.
                       Locations can be the same like for the profile (http,ftp,nfs,...).
                       <para>
                <screen>&lt;location&gt;http://10.10.0.1/myChrootScript.sh&lt;/location&gt;</screen>
                    </para></entry>
                <entry>either &lt;location&gt; or &lt;source&gt; must be defined</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>source</entry>
                <entry>the script itself. The source code of the script if you want so. Encapsulated in a CDATA tag. If you don't want
                to put the whole shell script into the XML profile, look at the location parameter.
                <para><screen>&lt;source&gt;
&lt;![CDATA[ 
echo "Testing the chroot script" &gt; /tmp/chroot_out.txt 
]]&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>either &lt;location&gt; or &lt;source&gt; must be defined</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>chrooted</entry>
                <entry>this value can be true or false. "False" means that the installed system is still mounted at "/mnt" and no chrooting has happened till now. The bootloader is not installed too at that stage. "True" means, we did a chroot into /mnt, so we are now in the installed system. The bootloader is installed and if you want to change anything in the installed system, you don't have to use the "/mnt/" prefix anymore.
                <para><screen>&lt;chrooted config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/chrooted&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional (the default is false)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>interpreter</entry>
                <entry>the interpreter that must be used for the script. Supported options are shell and perl.and if you are in a chrooted=true condition, you can use python too if it's installed.
                <para><screen>&lt;interpreter&gt;perl&lt;/interpreter&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional (default is shell)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>filename</entry>
                <entry>the filename of the script. It will be stored in a temporary directory under /tmp/...
                <para><screen>&lt;filename&gt;myPreScript5.sh&lt;/filename&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is the type of the script (pre-scripts) in this case</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>feedback</entry>
                <entry>if this boolean is true, stdout and stderr of the script will be shown in a popup that the
                       user has to confirm via ok-button. If stdout and stderr are empty, no popup is shown and so
                       no confirmation is needed.
                <para><screen>&lt;feedback config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/feedback&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is false. This option was invented with SL 10.1 / SLES10</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>debug</entry>
                <entry>if this is true, every single line of a shell script is logged. Perl scripts are run with warnings
                turned on.
                <para><screen>&lt;debug config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/debug&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is true. This option was invented with SL 10.1 / SLES10</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </para>
      </section>
    <section id="post-insall.scripts">
	<title>Post-Install Scripts</title>
	<para>
	  These scripts are executed after AutoYaST has completed the
	  system configuration and after it has booted the system for the first time.
	</para>
	<para>Starting from SLES9, network is not available during
	  post-installation script execution. To access the network, network
	  device has to be configured in the script.
	</para>
	<para>
	  It is possible to execute the post scripts in an earlier phase while
	  the installation network is still up and before AutoYaST configures
	  the system. To run network enabled post scripts, the boolean 
	  property <emphasis>network_needed</emphasis> has to be set to true.
	</para>
          <para>
            The following elements must be between the &lt;post-scripts config:type="list"&gt;&lt;script&gt; ... &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/post-scripts&gt; tags
          </para>
      <para>
        <table frame='top'>
          <title>post script XML representation</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Element</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
                <entry>Comment</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>location</entry>
                <entry>you can define a location from where the script gets fetched.
                       Locations can be the same like for the profile (http,ftp,nfs,...) but then you need a running network interface of course
                       <para>
                <screen>&lt;location&gt;http://10.10.0.1/myPostScript.sh&lt;/location&gt;</screen>
                    </para></entry>
                <entry>either &lt;location&gt; or &lt;source&gt; must be defined</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>source</entry>
                <entry>the script itself. The source code of the script if you want so. Encapsulated in a CDATA tag. If you don't want
                to put the whole shell script into the XML profile, look at the location parameter.
                <para><screen>&lt;source&gt;
&lt;![CDATA[ 
echo "Testing the chroot script" &gt; /tmp/chroot_out.txt 
]]&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>either &lt;location&gt; or &lt;source&gt; must be defined</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>network_needed</entry>
                <!-- FIXME: double check that. I'm very unsure if this is correct -->
                <entry>this value can be true or false. On "false" the script will run after the yast modules like the user configuration and everything else are done. The network is configured but still not up and running. With this value on "true", the script runs before(!) all yast modules are configured. So there is no local user and no network is configured but the installation network is still up and running (of course only if you did a network installation).
                <para><screen>&lt;network_needed config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/network_needed&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional (the default is false)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>interpreter</entry>
                <entry>the interpreter that must be used for the script. Supported options are shell, perl and python if it's installed.
                <para><screen>&lt;interpreter&gt;perl&lt;/interpreter&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional (default is shell)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>filename</entry>
                <entry>the filename of the script. It will be stored in a temporary directory under /tmp/...
                <para><screen>&lt;filename&gt;myPostScript5.sh&lt;/filename&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is the type of the script (post-scripts) in this case</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>feedback</entry>
                <entry>if this boolean is true, stdout and stderr of the script will be shown in a popup that the
                       user has to confirm via ok-button. If stdout and stderr are empty, no popup is shown and so
                       no confirmation is needed.
                <para><screen>&lt;feedback config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/feedback&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is false. This option was invented with SL 10.1 / SLES10</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>debug</entry>
                <entry>if this is true, every single line of a shell script is logged. Perl scripts are run with warnings
                turned on.
                <para><screen>&lt;debug config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/debug&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is true. This option was invented with SL 10.1 / SLES10</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="init.scripts">
	<title>Init Scripts</title>
	<note>
	  <para>Available starting from SLES9 only.</para>
	</note>
	<para>
	  These scripts are executed during the initial boot process and after
	  &yast2; has finished. The final scripts are executed using a special
	  <emphasis>init.d</emphasis> script which is executed only
	  once. The final scripts are executed toward the end of the boot
	  process and after network has been intialized.
	</para>
        <para>
            Init scripts are configured using the tag <emphasis>init-scripts</emphasis> and 
            are run using the special purpose <emphasis>init.d</emphasis> script <filename>/etc/init.d/autoyast</filename>.
        </para>
          <para>
            The following elements must be between the &lt;init-scripts config:type="list"&gt;&lt;script&gt; ... &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/init-scripts&gt; tags
          </para>
      <para>
        <table frame='top'>
          <title>init script XML representation</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Element</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
                <entry>Comment</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>location</entry>
                <entry>you can define a location from where the script gets fetched.
                       Locations can be the same like for the profile (http,ftp,nfs,...) but then you need a running network interface of course
                       <para>
                <screen>&lt;location&gt;http://10.10.0.1/myInitScript.sh&lt;/location&gt;</screen>
                    </para></entry>
                <entry>either &lt;location&gt; or &lt;source&gt; must be defined</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>source</entry>
                <entry>the script itself. The source code of the script if you want so. Encapsulated in a CDATA tag. If you don't want
                to put the whole shell script into the XML profile, look at the location parameter.
                <para><screen>&lt;source&gt;
&lt;![CDATA[ 
echo "Testing the init script" &gt; /tmp/init_out.txt 
]]&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>either &lt;location&gt; or &lt;source&gt; must be defined</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>filename</entry>
                <entry>the filename of the script. It will be stored in a temporary directory under /tmp/...
                <para><screen>&lt;filename&gt;mynitScript5.sh&lt;/filename&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is the type of the script (init-scripts) in this case</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </para>
    </section>
    <para>
      When added to the control file manually, the
      scripts have to be included in a <emphasis>CDATA</emphasis> element to avoid confusion with
      the file syntax and other tags defined in the control file.
    </para>
    <section id="script_examples">
    <title>Script example</title>
      <example>
	<title>Post script configuration</title>
	<screen>
    <xi:include href="examples/example.scripts.xml" parse="text"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

	</screen>
      </example>
    <para>
      After installation is finished, the scripts and the output logs can be
      found in the directory <filename>/var/adm/autoinstall</filename>. The
      scripts are located in <filename>scripts</filename> and the output logs of the
      scripts are located in the <filename>log</filename> directory.
    </para>
    <para>
      The log is the output resulting when executing the shell scripts using
      the following command:
    </para>
    <screen>
      <![CDATA[
      /bin/sh -x <script_name> 2&> /var/adm/autoinstall/logs/<script_name>.log
      ]]>
    </screen>
    </section>
  </section>


  <section id="createprofile.sysconfig">
    <title>System variables (Sysconfig)</title>
    <para>
      Using the sysconfig resource, it is possible to define configuration
      variables in the sysconfig repository
      (<filename>/etc/sysconfig</filename>) directly. Sysconfig
      variables, offer the possibility to fine-tune many system components and
      environment variables exactly to your needs.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Refer to  the handbook for more details about the many
      configuration options available in <filename>/etc/sysconfig</filename>
    </para>
    <para>
      The following example shows how a variable can be set using the sysconfig
      resource.
    </para>
    &example.sysconfig;
  </section>
  

  <section id="createprofile.completeconf">
    <title>Adding complete configurations</title>
    <para>
      For many applications and services you might have prepared a
      configuration file which should be copied in a complete form to some
      location in the installed system. This is for example if you are
      installing  a web server and have a <emphasis>ready to go</emphasis>
      server configuration file (<filename>httpd.conf</filename>).
    </para>
    <para>
      Using this resource, you can embed the file into the control file by
      specifying the final path on the installed system. &yast2; will copy this
      file to the specified location.
    </para>
    &example.files;

    <para>
      A more advanced example is shown below. This configuration will create
      a file using the content supplied in <emphasis>file_contents</emphasis>
      and will change the permissions and ownership of the file. After the
      file has been copied to the system, a script is executed which can be
      used to manipulate the file and prepare it for the environment of the client.
    </para>
    &example.filesadv;
  </section>


  <section id="CreateProfile.Hardware">
    <title>
      Miscellaneous hardware and system components
    </title>
    
    <para>
      In addition to the core component configuration, like network
      authentication and security, &autoyast;2 offers a wide range of
      hardware and system configuration which is available by default on
      any system installed manually and in an interactive way. For
      example, it is possible to configure printers, sound devices, TV
      cards and any other hardware components which have a module within YaST2.
    </para>
    <para>
      Any new configuration options that will be added to &yast2; will be
      automatically available as an auto-installation resource.
    </para>
    
    <section id="CreateProfile.Hardware.Printer">
      <title>
	Printer
      </title>

      <para>
	Although Printer configuration, like other configurations can be
	done manually, it is recommended to use the Configuration System to
	create such a configuration because of the complexity and the range
	of options offered by such modules.
      </para>
      <para>
	Using the configuration system will guarantee that the options
	provided are consistent. The following is an example of a
	configuration section which was
	created using the configuration system.
      </para>
      &example.printer;
    </section>

    <section id="CreateProfile.Hardware.Sound">
      <title>
	Sound devices
      </title>
      <para>
	An example of  sound configuration created using the configuration
	system is shown below.
      </para>
      &example.sound;
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="CreateProfile.Ask">
    <title>
      Ask the user for values during installation
    </title>

    <para>
        This feature is only available since SUSE Linux 10.1 and SLES10.
    </para>
    <para>
        You have the option to let the user decide the values of specific
        parts of the profile during the installation. If you use that feature,
        a popup will come up during the installation and will ask the user to
        enter a specific part of the profile. So if you want a full auto installation
        but you want the user to set the password of the local account, you can do
        this via the <emphasis>ask</emphasis> directive in the profile.
    </para>
          <para>
            The following elements must be between the &lt;ask-list config:type="list"&gt;&lt;ask&gt; ... &lt;/ask&gt;&lt;/ask-list&gt; tags in the &lt;general&gt; section.
          </para>
    <para>
        <table frame='top'>
          <title>XML representation</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Element</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
                <entry>Comment</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>question</entry>
                <entry>The question you want to ask the user.
                <para><screen>&lt;question&gt;Enter the LDAP server&lt;/question&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>The default value is the path to the element (the path often looks strange, so I recommend to enter a question)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>default</entry>
                <entry>you can set a pre-selection for the user. A textentry will be filled out with this value,
                       a checkbox will be "true" or "false" and a selection will have this default "value" pre-selected.
                <para><screen>&lt;default&gt;dc=suse,dc=de&lt;/default&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>help</entry>
                <entry>An optional helptext that is shown on the left side of the question.
                <para><screen>&lt;help&gt;Enter the LDAP server address.&lt;/help&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>title</entry>
                <entry>An optional title that is shown above the questions.
                <para><screen>&lt;title&gt;LDAP server&lt;/title&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>type</entry>
                <entry>the type of the element you want to change. Possible values are "symbol","boolean","string" and "integer". 
                       The filesystem in
                       the partition section is a symbol, while the "encrypted" element in the user configuration is a boolean.
                       You can see the type of that element if you look in your profile at the config:type="...." attribute.
                <para><screen>&lt;type&gt;symbol&lt;/type&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The defaul is string. If type is "symbol" you must provide the selection element too (see below)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>password</entry>
                <entry>if this boolean is set to "true", a password dialog pops up instead of a simple text entry. Setting this
                       to "true" makes only sense if "type" is string.
                <para><screen>&lt;password config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/password&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is "false"</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>path</entry>
                <entry>The path to the element in the profile. It's a comma seperated list of elements that describes the
                       path to the element you want to change. For example, the ldap server element can be found in the profile
                       in the &lt;ldap&gt;&lt;ldap_server&gt; section. So if you want to change that value, you have to set the
                       path to "ldap,ldap_server". If you want to change the password of the first user in the profile, you have to
                       set the path to "users,0,user_password". The "0" indicates the first user in the &lt;users config:type="list"&gt;
                       list of users in the profile.
                <para><screen>&lt;path&gt;networking,dns,hostname&lt;/path&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>this information is optional but you should at least provie <emphasis>path</emphasis> or <emphasis>file</emphasis></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>file (available since SLES10 SP1 and SL 10.2)</entry>
                <entry>you can store the answer to a question in a file, to use it in one of your scripts later.
                <para><screen>&lt;file&gt;/tmp/answer_hostname&lt;/file&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>this information is optional but you should at least provie <emphasis>path</emphasis> or <emphasis>file</emphasis></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>password</entry>
                <entry>if this boolean is set to "true", a password dialog pops up instead of a simple text entry. Setting this
                       to "true" makes only sense if "type" is string.
                <para><screen>&lt;password config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/password&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is "false"</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>stage</entry>
                <entry>stage configures the installation stage where the question pops up. You can set this value to "cont" or
                       "initial". "initial" means the popup comes up very early in the installation, short after the pre-script
                       has run. "cont" means, that the dialog with the question comes after the first reboot, when the system
                       boots for the very first time. Questions you answer during the "inital" stage, will write their answer
                       into the profile on the harddisk. You should know that if you enter cleartext passwords during "initial".
                       Of course it does not make sense to ask for a filesystem to use in the "cont" phase. The harddisk is already
                       partitioned at that stage and the question will have no effect.
                <para><screen>&lt;stage&gt;cont&lt;/stage&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional. The default is "initial"</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>selection</entry>
                <entry>the selection element contains a list of &lt;entry&gt; elements. Each entry represents a possible option
                       for the user to choose. So the user can't enter a value in a textfield, but he can choose from a list
                       of values.
                <para><screen>
&lt;selection config:type="list"&gt;
  &lt;entry&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
        reiser
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;
        Reiser Filesystem
    &lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;/entry&gt;
  &lt;entry&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
        ext3
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;
        Extended3 Filesystem
    &lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;/entry&gt;
&lt;/selection&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional for type=string, not possible for type=boolean and a must have for type=symbol</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>dialog (available since SL 10.3 not in SLES10 SP1)</entry>
                <entry>Since OpenSUSE 10.3 you can have more than one question per dialog. To make that possible you have
                to specifiy the dialog-id with an integer. All questions with the same dialog-id are on the same dialog.
                The dialogs are sorted by the id too.
                <para><screen>&lt;dialog config:type="integer"&gt;3&lt;/dialog&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>element (available since SL 10.3 not in SLES10 SP1)</entry>
                <entry>Since OpenSUSE 10.3 you can have more than one question per dialog. To make that possible you have
                to specifiy the element-id with an integer. The questions on a dialog are sorted by the id.
                <para><screen>&lt;element config:type="integer"&gt;1&lt;/element&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional (see dialog></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>frametitle (available since SL 10.3 not in SLES10 SP1)</entry>
                <entry>Since OpenSUSE 10.3 you can have more than one question per dialog. Each question on a dialog has
                a frame that can have a frametitle. A small caption for each question if you want so.
                <para><screen>&lt;frametitle&gt;User data&lt;/frametitle&gt;</screen></para></entry>
                <entry>optional (default is no frametitle)</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>

        </table>
    </para>
    <para>
      Below you can see an example of the usage of the "ask" feature.
    </para>
    <para>
      <screen>
&lt;general&gt;
  &lt;ask-list config:type=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
      &lt;ask&gt;
          &lt;path&gt;ldap,ldap_server&lt;/path&gt;
          &lt;stage&gt;cont&lt;/stage&gt;
          &lt;help&gt;choose your server depending on your department&lt;/help&gt;
          &lt;selection config:type=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
              &lt;entry&gt;
                      &lt;value&gt;ldap1.mydom.de&lt;/value&gt;
                      &lt;label&gt;LDAP for development&lt;/label&gt;
              &lt;/entry&gt;
              &lt;entry&gt;
                      &lt;value&gt;ldap2.mydom.de&lt;/value&gt;
                      &lt;label&gt;LDAP for sales&lt;/label&gt;
              &lt;/entry&gt;
          &lt;/selection&gt;
          &lt;default&gt;ldap2.mydom.de&lt;/default&gt;
      &lt;/ask&gt;
      &lt;ask&gt;
          &lt;path&gt;networking,dns,hostname&lt;/path&gt;
          &lt;question&gt;Enter Hostname&lt;/question&gt;
          &lt;stage&gt;initial&lt;/stage&gt;
          &lt;default&gt;enter your hostname here&lt;/default&gt;
      &lt;/ask&gt;
      &lt;ask&gt;
          &lt;path&gt;partitioning,0,partitions,0,filesystem&lt;/path&gt;
          &lt;question&gt;Filesystem&lt;/question&gt;
          &lt;type&gt;symbol&lt;/type&gt;
          &lt;selection config:type=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
              &lt;entry&gt;
                      &lt;value config:type=&quot;symbol&quot;&gt;reiser&lt;/value&gt;
                      &lt;label&gt;default Filesystem (recommended)&lt;/label&gt;
              &lt;/entry&gt;
              &lt;entry&gt;
                      &lt;value config:type=&quot;symbol&quot;&gt;ext3&lt;/value&gt;
                      &lt;label&gt;Fallback Filesystem&lt;/label&gt;
              &lt;/entry&gt;
          &lt;/selection&gt;

      &lt;/ask&gt;
  &lt;/ask-list&gt;
  ...
&lt;/general&gt;
</screen>
</para>
  </section>

  </chapter>
  <!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: xml
  sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast.xml" "book" "chaper")
  End:
  -->
