
<chapter id="Invoking">
  <title>The Auto-Installation Process</title>
  <section id="Installation.process">
    
    <title>
      Introduction
    </title>
    <para>
      After the system has booted and the control file has been retrieved,
      &yast2; performs configuration of the system according to the information
      provided in the  control file. All the configuration is summarized in a window that is shown by
      default and should be deactivated if a full automatic installation is
      needed.      
    </para>
    <para>
      When &yast2; has  reached the point where the summary of the configuration is shown,
      &yast2; has only probed hardware and prepared the system for
      auto-installation, thus, nothing has been changed in the system yet, so
      that in case of any error, the process still can be aborted.
    </para>
        
    <para>
      A system should be automatically installable without the need to have
      any graphic adaptor or monitor. Having a monitor attached to the
      client machine is nevertheless recommended to follow the process and
      to get feedback in case of any errors. Choosing between the Qt and the
      Ncurses interfaces is possible. For headless
      clients, system messages can be monitored using the serial console.
    </para>
    <section id="Installation.Interface.X11">
      <title>
	X11 Interface
      </title>
      <para>
	This is the  default interface while auto-installing. No special
	variables are required to activate it.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="Installation.Interface.SerialConsole">
      <title>
	Serial console
      </title>
      <para>
	You can start installing a system using the serial console by adding
	the keyword console (i.e. console=ttyS0) to the command line of the
	kernel. This will start linuxrc in console mode and later in the
	process, &yast2; also is started in serial console mode.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="Installation.Interface.Ncurses">
      <title>
	Text based YaST2-Installation
      </title>
      <para>
	This option can also be activated on the command line. This will start
	YaST2 in <emphasis>Ncurses</emphasis> mode. To start &yast2; in text
	mode, add <emphasis>textmode=1</emphasis> on the command line.
      </para>
      <para>
	Starting &yast2; in text mode is recommended when installing  a client
	with less than 64 MB or when X11 is not being configured at all,
	especially on headless machines.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="bootmedium">
    <title>Choosing the right Boot Medium</title>
    <para>
      There are different methods for booting the client. The computer can boot from
      its network interface card (NIC) to receive the boot images via  &dhcp; /TFTP
      or a suitable kernel as well as an initrd image are loaded from a
      floppy or a boot-able CD-ROM. 
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>
	Booting from a floppy
      </title>
      <para>
	For testing/rescue purposes or because the NIC does not have a PROM or PXE
	you can build a boot floppy to use with &autoyast2;. Using a floppy
	to initiate an auto-install process is limited due to the size of the
	data a floppy can hold. However, it is still  possible to use
	floppies when auto-installing a single, disconnected machine.
      </para>
      <para>
	Floppies can be used to store the control file, especially when using
	the original  &company-suse;  CD-ROMs for a single, disconnected machine. Using the
	kernel command line, you can specify the location of the control
	file on the floppy.
      </para>
      <para>
	Even without specifying any command line options, it is still possible to initiate the
	auto-install process by placing a control file on a floppy with a
	special, pre-defined file name. (<filename>autoinst.xml</filename>) &yast2; will check for
	<filename>autoinst.xml</filename> upon startup and if it was found it
	will switch from interactive to automated installation.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Booting from CD-ROM</title>
      <para>
	You can use the original  &company-suse;  CD-ROMs in combination with other
	media, i.e. with a floppy to hold the control file or in combination
	with network where the control file can be located.
      </para>
      <para>
	It is also possible to create customized CD-ROMs to hold only the
	package you need in addition to the control file which also can be
	saved on the CD-ROM. This method requires creation of CD-ROMs
	every time you wish to change the configuration though.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="invoking_autoinst">
    <title id="invoking_autoinst.title">
      Invoking the Auto-Installation process
    </title>

    <section>
      <title>Command line Options</title>
      <para>
	Adding the command line variable <emphasis>autoyast</emphasis> will make
	<emphasis>linuxrc</emphasis> start  in automated mode.
	<command>Linuxrc</command> searches for a configuration file, which
	should be distinguished from the main control file in the following
	places:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>In the root directory of the initial ram-disk used for booting
	    the system up</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>In the root directory of the floppy</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	The configuration file used by <command>linuxrc</command> can have the
	following keywords (for a detailed description of how linuxrc works and
	other keywords, see <quote><link linkend='appendix.linuxrc'
	    endterm="appendix.linuxrc.title"></link></quote> ):
      </para>   
      
      <table frame='top'>
	<title>Keywords for <command>linuxrc</command></title>
	<tgroup cols='2'>
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Keyword</entry>
	      <entry>Value</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  
	  
	  <tbody>
	    
	    <row><entry>netdevice</entry><entry>Which network device to use for
		network setup (Device used for  &bootp; / &dhcp;  requests)</entry></row> 
	    <row><entry>server</entry><entry>Which server to contact for source directory (NFS Server)</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>serverdir</entry><entry>Directory on NFS Server </entry></row>
	    <row><entry>hostip</entry><entry>When empty, client sends  &bootp;  request, otherwise client is configured with entered IP configuration.</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>netmask</entry><entry>Netmask</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>gateway</entry><entry>Gateway</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>nameserver</entry><entry>Nameserver</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>insmod</entry><entry>Kernel modules to load.</entry></row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>autoyast</entry>
	      <entry>Location of the the control file to be used for the
		automatic installation, i.e
		<emphasis>autoyast=http://192.168.2.1/profiles/</emphasis></entry>

	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>install</entry>
	      <entry>Location of the installation directory, i.e. <emphasis>install=nfs://192.168.2.1/CDs/</emphasis> </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>instmode</entry>
	      <entry>Installation mode, i.e. nfs, http etc. (Not needed if
		<emphasis>install</emphasis> is set)</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      
      
      
      <para>
	These variables and keywords will bring the system up to the point
	where &yast2; can take over with the main control file. Currently, the
	source medium is
	automatically discovered, which in some cases makes it possible to
	initiate the auto-install process without giving any instructions to
	linuxrc.
      </para>

      <para>
	The traditional <command>linuxrc</command> configuration file
	(<filename>info</filename>) 
	should be used only in the  preparation phase and has the function of
	giving the client enough information about the installation server and
	the location of the sources. In most cases this file is not needed; it is however
	needed in special network  environments where  &dhcp; / &bootp;  are not
	used or when special kernel modules  have to be loaded.      
      </para>
      <para>
	All linuxrc keywords 
	can be passed to <command>linuxrc</command> using the kernel command
	line.  The   command line can  for example also be set when creating network boot-able
	images or it can be passed to the kernel using a specially configured
	&dhcp;  server in combination with Etherboot or &pxe;.
      </para>
      <para>	
	The format of the special  command line variable
	<emphasis>autoyast</emphasis> can be used as described in table  <quote><link
	    linkend="commandLineAutoYaST" endterm="commandLineAutoYaST.title"></link></quote>
      </para>
      
      <table frame='top' id="commandLineAutoYaST">
	<title id="commandLineAutoYaST.title">Command line variables for AutoYaST</title>
	<tgroup cols='2'>
	  <thead>	  
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Command line variable
	      </entry><entry>Description</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>	
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>autoyast=default</entry><entry>Default auto-installation option </entry></row>
	    <row><entry>autoyast=file:/&lt;path&gt;</entry><entry>Looks for
		control  file in specified path (relative to source root
		directory, i.e. <emphasis>file:/autoinst.xml</emphasis> if in
		the top directory of a CD-ROM )</entry></row>
	    
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		autoyast=device://&lt;device&gt;/&lt;file&gt;</entry><entry>Looks
		for control file on a storage device. (only device name needed
		without full path, i.e. /dev/sda1 is wrong, instead use sda1)
	      </entry>
	    </row>

	    
	    <row>
	      <entry>autoyast=floppy:/&lt;path&gt;</entry>
	      <entry>Looks for  control file in the floppy (Useful when booting
		from CD)</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>autoyast=nfs://&lt;server&gt;/&lt;path&gt;</entry>
	      <entry>Looks for control file on &lt;server&gt; </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>autoyast=http://&lt;server&gt;/&lt;path&gt;</entry>
	      <entry>Retrieves the  control file  from a web server using the HTTP protocol.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>autoyast=tftp://&lt;server&gt;/&lt;path&gt;</entry>
	      <entry>Retrieve the control file with TFTP</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>autoyast=ftp://&lt;server&gt;/&lt;path&gt;</entry>
	      <entry>Retrieve the control file with FTP</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
	Several scenarios for auto-installation are possible using different
	types of infrastructure and source media. The simplest way is by using
	the source media from the  &company-suse;  Box. In that case you have
	either a DVD with all  &company-suse;  packages or a set of CD-ROMs. To initiate the
	auto-installation process however, the auto-installation command line
	variable should be entered at system boot-up and the control file should
	be accessible to YaST2. The following list of scenarios explains how
	the control file can be supplied and the setup needed for the
	auto-installation process to be successful.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Using  &company-suse;  original CD-ROMs from  &company-suse;  Linux box:
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    To use the original CD-ROMs, you need a media with the control
	    file, the control file can reside on the following locations:
	  </para>
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Floppy</emphasis>: Control file accessible via the
		<emphasis>autoyast=floppy</emphasis> option. &yast2; also searches
		upon startup for a file named
		<filename>autoinst.xml</filename>. If such a file is found, YaST2
		will switch into auto-installation mode even if no special
		command line variables were supplied.  (See <quote><link
		    linkend="autoinstall.singlesystem"
		    endterm="autoinstall.singlesystem.title"></link></quote> )
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Network</emphasis>: Control file accessible via the
		<emphasis>autoyast=nfs://..</emphasis>,
		<emphasis>autoyast=ftp://..</emphasis>
		<emphasis>autoyast=http://..</emphasis> or
		<emphasis>autoyast=tftp://..</emphasis> options.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	  </orderedlist>	  
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>	    
	    Using 'self-made' CD-ROMs:
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    In this case, you can include the control file on the CD-ROM
	    for easy access (using the <emphasis>autoyast=file://</emphasis>
	    option) or use one of the above mentioned methods used with the 
	    original  &company-suse;  CD-ROMs.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Using NFS and Floppy, Network or CD-ROM for system boot-up.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This option is the most important one due to the fact that
	    installations of PC farms are normally done using NFS servers and other
	    network services like  &bootp; / &dhcp; . The control file can reside in
	    the following places:	    
	  </para>
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Floppy/CD-ROM</emphasis>: Control file accessible via the
		<emphasis>autoyast=file:/..</emphasis> option.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Network</emphasis>: Control file accessible via the
		<emphasis>autoyast=http://..</emphasis>,
		<emphasis>autoyast=ftp://..</emphasis>,
		<emphasis>autoyast=nfs://..</emphasis> or
		<emphasis>autoyast=tftp://..</emphasis> options.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	  </orderedlist>	  	 
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
      

      <para>
	If <emphasis>autoyast=default</emphasis> is defined, &yast2; will look
	for a file named <filename>autoinst.xml</filename> in
	the following three places: 
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The root directory of the floppy disk.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The root directory of the installation medium.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The root directory of the initial ram disk used to boot the system.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>
	With all autoyast invocation options, excluding
	<emphasis>default</emphasis>, it is possible to specify the location of
	the control file in the following ways:
      </para>

      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify the exact location of the control file:
	    <screen>
autoyast=http://192.168.1.1/control-files/client01.xml
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify a directory where several control files are located
	  </para>
	  <screen>
autoyast=http://192.168.1.1/control-files/
	  </screen>
	  <para>
	    In this case the relevant control file is retrieved using the hex digit
	    representation of the IP as described below.
	  </para>	    	    
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>	
	If only the path prefix variable is defined, &yast2; will fetch the
	control file from the specified location in the following way:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    First, it will search for the control file using its own IP address in
	    upper case hexadecimal, e.g. <emphasis>192.0.2.91 -> C000025B</emphasis>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If that file is not found, it will remove one hex digit and try
	    again. This action is repeated till the file with the correct name
	    is found.  Ultimately, it will try looking for a file with the MAC
	    address of the clients as the file name (mac should have the
	    following syntax: <emphasis>0080C8F6484C</emphasis>) and if not found a file named 
	    <filename>default</filename> (in lower
	    case).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    
    <para>
      As an example, for 192.0.2.91, the HTTP client will try:
      </para>
    <literallayout>      
C000025B
C000025
C00002
C0000
C000
C00
C0
C
0080C8F6484C
default
    </literallayout>
    <para>
      in that order. 
      </para>
      <para>
	To determine the hex representation of the IP address of the client,
	use the utility called <command>/usr/sbin/gethostip</command> available
	with the <emphasis>syslinux</emphasis> package.
      </para>
      <example>
	<title>Determine HEX code for an IP address</title>
	<screen>
# /usr/sbin/gethostip 10.10.0.1
10.10.0.1 10.10.0.1 0A0A0001
	</screen>
      </example>



    </section>

    <section id="autoinstall.singlesystem">
      <title id="autoinstall.singlesystem.title">
	Auto-installing a Single System
      </title>
      <para>
	The easiest way to auto-install a system  without any network connection
	is by using the standard CD-ROMs that come in the  &company-suse;  Linux box. Using the
	CD-ROMs in combination with  a floppy disk  lets you getting started with
	&autoyast2; very fast and without spending much time configuring
	installation server  and network environments.
      </para>


      <para>
	Create the control file and
	name it <filename>autoinst.xml</filename>. Copy the file
	<filename>autoinst.xml</filename> to a floppy by either mounting the
	floppy or by using the <emphasis>mtools</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <screen>
mcopy autoinst.xml a:
      </screen>

    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Combining linuxrc <emphasis>info</emphasis> file with &yast2; control file</title>
      <para>
	If you choose to pass information to  <emphasis>linuxrc</emphasis> using
	the <emphasis>info</emphasis> file, it is possible to integrate the
	keywords in the XML control file. In the case the file has to be
	accessible to linuxrc and has to be named <emphasis>info</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
	Linuxrc will look for a string (<emphasis>start_linuxrc_conf</emphasis>
	in the control file which represents the
	beginning of the file. If it is found, it will parse the content starting
	from that string and will finish when the string
	<emphasis>end_linuxrc_conf</emphasis> is found. The options are stored in
	the control file in the following way:
      </para>
      <example>
	<title>
	  Linxurc options in the control file
	</title>
	<screen>
	  <![CDATA[
....
  <install>
....
    <init>
      <info_file>
<![CDATA[
#
# Don't remove the following line:
# start_linuxrc_conf
#
install: nfs://192.168.1.1/CDs/full-i386
textmode: 1
autoyast: file:///info

# end_linuxrc_conf
# Do not remove the above comment
#
]]]><![CDATA[]>

      </info_file>
    </init>
......
  </install>
....
]]>
	</screen>
      </example>
      <para>
	Note that the autoyast keyword must point to the same file, i.e. if it
	is on a floppy, then the protocol <emphasis>floppy</emphasis> has to be
	used. In other cases where the <emphasis>info</emphasis> file is stored
	in the initial ram-disk, the <emphasis>file</emphasis> option has to be used.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="System_Configuration">    
    <title id="System_Configuration.title">
      System Configuration 
    </title>
    <para>
      The system configuration during auto-installation can be seen as the
      most important part of the whole process. Customizing a system to your
      environment needs is what makes an auto-installation system attractive,
      not the installation part.
    </para>
    <para>
      As you have seen in the previous chapters, almost anything can be
      configured automatically on the target system. In addition to the
      pre-defined directives, you can always  use post-scripts to change other
      things in the system. Additionally you can change any system variables and
      if required, copy complete configuration files into the target system.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>
	Post-Install and System Configuration
      </title>
      <para>
	The Post-Installation and the System Configuration are initiated directly after the last
	package is installed in the target system  and is continued after the
	system has booted for the first time.
      </para>
      <para>
	Before the system is booted for the first time, &yast2; writes all data
	collected during installation into the system and finally it writes the
	boot loader in the specified location. In addition to these regular
	tasks, which are also done when performing a regular installation, YaST2
	executes the <emphasis>chroot-scripts</emphasis> as specified in the
	control file. Note that these scripts are executed while the system is
	still not mounted.
      </para>      
      <para>
	If a different kernel than the default is installed, a hard reboot will
	be required. A hard reboot can also be forced during auto-installation,
	independent of the installed kernel. This can be accomplished using the
	<emphasis>reboot</emphasis> property of the
	<emphasis>general</emphasis> resource. (See <link
	  linkend="CreateProfile.General">General Options</link>)
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>System Customization</title>
      <para>
	Most of the system customization is done in the second stage of the
	installation. &yast2; provides most of the important resources needed to
	bring up  a system to a usable , general state. However, you may have
	other requirements for the installed system. If the required
	customizations can't be done using &yast2; resources, then the
	post-install scripts can be used to accomplish this task.
      </para>
      <para>
	You can define an unlimited number of custom scripts in the control
	file either by editing the control file or by using the configuration
	system.	
      </para>      
    </section>
  </section>

  </chapter>


 
      <!--
       Local Variables:
       mode: xml
       sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "chapter")
       End:
      --> 
