

<chapter id="Installation">
  <title>Starting Auto-Installation</title>
  <sect1 id="Installation.process">
    
    <title>
      The Auto-Installation Process
    </title>
    <para>
      After the system has booted and the control file has been retrieved,
      &yast2; performs configuration of the system according to the information
      contained in the  control
      file. All the configuration is summarized in a window that is shown by
      default and should be deactivated if a full automatic installation is
      needed.      
    </para>
    <para>
      When reaching the point where the summary of the configuration is shown,
      &yast2; has only probed hardware and prepared the system for
      auto-installation, thus, nothing has been changed in the system yet, so
      that in case of any error, the process still can be aborted.
    </para>
    
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="Installation.Interface">
    <title>
      Interface during Auto-Install
    </title>
    <para>
      A system should be automatically install-able without the need to have
      any graphic adaptor or monitor. Having a monitor attached to the
      client machine is nevertheless recommended to follow the process and
      to get feedback in case of any errors. Choosing between the Qt and the
      Ncurses interfaces is possible. For headless
      clients, system messages can be monitored using the serial console.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="Installation.Interface.X11">
      <title>
	X11 Interface
      </title>
      <para>
	This is the  default interface while auto-installing. No special
	variables are required to activate it.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="Installation.Interface.SerialConsole">
      <title>
	Serial console
      </title>
      <para>
	You can start installing a system using the serial console by adding
	the keyword console (i.e. console=ttyS0) to the command line of the
	kernel. This will start linuxrc in console mode and later in the
	process, &yast2; also is started in serial console mode.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="Installation.Interface.Ncurses">
      <title>
	Text based YaST2-Installation
      </title>
      <para>
	This option can also be activated on the command line. This will start
	YaST2 in <emphasis>Ncurses</emphasis> mode. To start &yast2; in text
	mode, add <emphasis>textmode=1</emphasis> on the command line.
      </para>
      <para>
	Starting &yast2; in text mode is recommended when installing  a client
	with less than 64 MB or when X11 is not being configured at all,
	especially on headless machines.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  </chapter>
      <!--
       Local Variables:
       mode: xml
       sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "chapter")
       End:
      -->  
