  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    
    <para>
      In order to ease and automate Linux installations,  &company-suse;
      offers AutoYaST2, which lets the user create a configuration for a single
      system or a set of systems  and automatically performs the installation
      relying on a control file which can be provided to &yast2; during
      installation in different ways.
    </para>  
    	&IntroductionLinuxJournal;
    <para>
      Using AutoYaST2, multiple systems sharing the same environment and
      hardware performing similar tasks can easily be installed in parallel. A
      configuration  file (referred to as "control  file") is created using
      existing configuration resources. The control file can be easily tailored for any
      specific environment. 
      </para>
    <para>
      Unlike autoinstallation systems available with older &company-suse;
      releases, &autoyast2 is fully integrated and provides various options for
      installing and configuring a system. The important advantage over older
      systems and other autoinstall systems is the possibility to configure the
      system by using existing modules and not by using custom scripts which
      are normally executed at the end of the installation.
    how </para>

      <para>
      The following chapters will guide you through the three steps of
      auto-installation:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Prepare: All relevant information about the target system is
  collected and turned into the appropriate directives of the control
  file. The control file is transferred onto the target system where
  its directives will be parsed and transformed to &yast2; conforming
	  data. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Install:  follows the instructions given in the  control file and
	  installs a base system.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Configure:  &yast2; and some user-defined post-install
	  scripts accomplish the system configuration
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure id="process">
      <title id="process.title">Auto-installation process</title>
      <mediaobject>&autoyast-oview;</mediaobject>
    </figure>




<!--
    <tip>
    <para>
      Auto-Installation is  interesting when installing large number
      of machines which at least have one thing in common. For example
      auto-installation can be used for installing a network of workstations
      which share the same environment and have similar hardware and will be
      performing similar tasks.
    </para>
    </tip>
   -->
    
  </chapter>



  <!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: xml
  sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "book")
  End:
  -->

