<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"/usr/share/xml/db41xml/docbookx.dtd"[]>

  <article>
  <articleinfo>    
    <title>AutoYaST2: SLES Network Installation</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Anas</firstname>
      <surname>Nashif</surname>
    </author>    
  </articleinfo>
  <para>
    Creating NFS directory for UL/SLES from distribution CDs
  </para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      UnitedLinux defines a core set of packages which implement the UnitedLinux runtime environment.
      All tests, certifications, and applications are based on this set of packages
      which should not be altered in any way. The ideal way to guarantee
      unaltered data, is providing it on CD-ROM.
    </para>
    <para>
      However, this makes including (vendor specific) extensions and bug-fixes on
      the same media impossible. A separate media must be supplied for
      installation.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <emphasis>multiple source</emphasis> approach of YaST gives a solution as it allows
      installation from several (package) sources. So a customer can start
      installing from the original UnitedLinux CDs, proceed with a product CD,
      and end with a patch CD containing the latest security patches.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>
      The installer source
    </title>
    <para>
      When starting the installation from a media (CD, DVD, NFS, ...), linuxrc looks
      for a <filename>/boot/root</filename> file containing a complete
      (cramfs based) root filesystem for YaST.
    </para>

    <para>
      Usually, this file is on the boot CD, but other installation types are
      also supported by linuxrc. The information, where the <filename>/boot/root</filename> file
      came from, is passed to YaST and defines the installer source. 	
    </para>
    <para>	
      YaST now looks at this installer source for a <filename>/yast/order</filename> file. If this
      file exists, YaST goes into the <emphasis>multiple installation</emphasis> mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      In this mode, the source description (information about the packages) is on
      the installer source and the source data (the rpm packages itself) is
      on separate media.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the order file does not exist, YaST does not separate the source
      description from the source data and both must reside on the same
      media. (The latter is what happens if you boot the first UnitedLinux
      CD.)
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>File Structure on Installation CDs</title>
      <para>
	The following illustration shows the CD structure of the SLES CD.
      </para>
 
      <screen>
.
|-- boot
|   `-- loader
|-- docu
|   `-- HOWTOs
|-- media.1
|-- suse
|   |-- i586
|   |-- noarch
|   |-- nosrc
|   |-- setup
|   |   |-- descr
|   |   `-- slide
|   `-- src
`-- yast
    `-- ul
        |-- UnitedLinux
        `-- media.1

      </screen>

      <para>
	The media and product description is splitted to a set of files,
	separating the media preparation data from the contents (product) and
	making it possible to combine several products on a single media.
      </para>
      <para>
	At toplevel of a media, a directory <filename>/media.1/</filename> should exists.
	If it does not exist, the presence of the correct media can not be
	verified. This may be convenient for an on-line media which just
	provides a set of packages.
      </para>
      <para>
	In this case, no verfication takes place. The numeric extension depends
	on the media number in case of splitted medias. The first media has .1,
	the second .2, and so on.
      </para>
      <para>
	This allows merging all medias of a splitted set into a single
	directory. YaST always knows which media to expect and can thereby
	directly access the correct media directory.
      </para>
      <section>
	<title>Files inside boot/</title>
	<para>
	  the directory boot/ contains installation images and floppy images
	  that can be used to create boot and installation floppies. The
	  <filename>root</filename> files contains a complete
	  (cramfs based) root filesystem for YaST. This file contains the
	  actual installer. The <filename>root</filename> file is fetched by
	  <command>linuxrc</command> from the installation source and is
	  mounted in the installtion environment. <command>Linuxrc</command>
	  starts the installer from within this file.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The directory <filename>boot/loader</filename> contains the kernel
	  and the initial ramdisk  used for installation. It also contains the
	  isolinux files used for creating the CD.
	</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	<title>Files inside media.N/</title>
	<para>
	  Inside the media.N/ directory the files media and products must
	  exist. Optionally, a file named patches may exist to denote a media
	  with patches (e.g. for YaST online update).
	</para>
     
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The /media.N/media file</para>
	    <para>
	      The media file contains the media identifier needed to determine
	      correctness when using removable media.	
	      In case of splitted media, it must be present on every media of the
	      set.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      This should contain a key to quickly identify correctness of the inserted
	      media. It is not shown to the user but should contain human-readable data
	      for debugging purposes.	      
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>The products file</para>
	    <para>
	      The products file contains directory specifications for each product.
	      In case of splitted media, it must be present of the first media of the set.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The patches file</para>
	    <para>
	      The patches file contains a single directory specification for the root
	      of the patches directory tree.	
	      In case of splitted media, it must be present of the first media of the set.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The info.txt file</para>
	    <para>
	      This file contains any licensing information that should be
	      presented to the user when YaST is started. If not present, no
	      license screen is shown. On the SLES CD, it contains the EULA.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
       	
 
	<para>	
	  The identification data is stored inside the file on purpose. It could
	  also be encoded in the file name (older SuSE media did it). But this
	  requires a directory scan for file access and should be avoided.
	</para>
	<para>	By storing the vendor name in the file, the timestamp can be kept
	  vendor specific. (It's the name of the vendor who created the media
	  which might be different from a product vendor! It's just used as an
	  additional key for media identification.)
	</para>
	<para>
	  The media count is needed if the installation data is split up on
	  multiple (identical) medias. The media file on the first media should
	  contain the total count of medias.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The media count is a numerical value (all characters are digits).
	  It is an optional information on the other media.
	</para>
	<para>	
	  A forth line may contain flags further describing the media. n order to
	  distinguish the flags from the count line, the flags values start with
	  a letter.
	</para>
	<para>
	  All media of a media-set must have identical vendor and data
	  information in the media file.
	</para>

	<example>
	  <title>media directory</title>
	  <screen>
# ls -1 media.1
info.txt
media
products
	  
# cat media.1/media
SuSE Linux AG
20021022191434
1

# cat media.1/products
/ SuSE-Linux-SLES-i386 8
 
	  </screen>
	</example>

      </section>    
      <section>
	<title>The contents files</title>
	<para>
	  This file resides inside the product directory as specified by the
	  products file on the media. It contains all product-specfic data to
	  describe and identify the contents of the product. If there was no
	  products file, the product directory defaults to the root directory
	  on the media.
	  </para>
	<para>
	  The content file might be missing if the media does not contain a
	  product (but just a set of packages).	  
	</para>

	<example>
	  <title>The contents file</title>
	  <para>
	    <screen>
# cat content
PRODUCT SuSE SLES
VERSION 8
DISTPRODUCT SuSE-Linux-SLES-i386
DISTVERSION 8.1-0
BASEPRODUCT UnitedLinux
BASEVERSION 1.0
YOUTYPE business
YOUPATH i386/update/SuSE-SLES/8
YOUURL http://www.suse.de/cgi-bin/suseservers.cgi
VENDOR SuSE Linux AG
ARCH.i686 i686 i586 i486 i386 noarch
ARCH.i586 i586 i486 i386 noarch
ARCH.i486 i486 i386 noarch
ARCH.i386 i386 noarch
DEFAULTBASE i386
REQUIRES distribution-release
LINGUAS de en
LABEL SuSE SLES Version 8
LABEL.de SuSE SLES in der Version 8
DESCRDIR suse/setup/descr
DATADIR suse
LANGUAGE en_US
TIMEZONE America/Los_Angeles

</screen>
	  </para>
	</example>
      </section>
   

  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>
      The order file
    </title>
    <para> 
      The order file defines which sources are needed for installation and their priority for installation.
      A typical example for an order file is given here:
    </para>
    <screen>
# yast/order: priority of installation sources
#
# source-       product
# description   path
/yast/sles8     /sles8-i386/CD1
/yast/ul        /unitedlinux-i386/CD1
/               /
    </screen>

    <para> 
      The order file is ASCII, line based, '#' at the beginning of a
      line denote a comment line.
    </para>    
    <para> 
      Each non-comment line should contain two (tab separated)
      directory specifications. If the second one is omitted, it defaults to
      "/".
    </para>
    <para> 
      The first directory specifies the location of the description.
      The second directory specifies the location of the product as defined here.
      For CD/DVD bases products, this is usually "/". But for network installations,
      or if several product are placed on a single CD, each product needs a
      separate path.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can even specify a full URL (e.g. "nfs://my-nfs-server.domain.org/product/CD1") in the second column. 
      During installation, you can't switch the type of media. If your
      installer source is CD, every other source must be CD based. If your
      installer source is NFS, every other source is expected to be on the
      same NFS server.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the above example of the order file, note the last line being
      "/". This means the last of the three installation sources is on the
      same media as the installer.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>
      The instorder file
    </title>
    <para>
      As stated above, the <filename>/yast/order</filename> file lists the sources in priority
      order. So a package from a source listed earlier in this file
      overrides a package (of the same name) from a later source. This
      technique is used to override the yast2-translation packages from
      unitedlinux-i386 (where all help texts refer to UnitedLinux) with
      yast2-translation packages from sles8-i386 (where all help texts
      refer to SuSE Linux).
    </para>
    <para>
      
      But the <filename>/yast/order</filename> also defines the installation
      order, which might not be wanted when the 'base' packages are on a
      lower-priority source.
    </para>
    <para>
      This is where <filename>/yast/instorder</filename> comes into play. This defines the installation
      order by repeating the entries of the first column of <filename>/yast/order</filename> in
      the right order.
    </para>

    

    <para>
      A typical example for an instorder file is given here:
    </para>
    <screen>
# yast/instorder: order of installation sources
#
# install 'ul' before 'sles8'
#
/yast/ul
/yast/sles8
/
    </screen>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>

    <title>Setting it all up</title>

    <para> 
      Combining multiple sources requires that all sources comply to
      the UnitedLinux media description standard.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the source directory, copy all SLES and UL into seperate directories
      (CDs can also be copied into one single directory, but to keep a clean
      structure, CDs can be copied into seperate directories, i.e. using the
      following scheme: UL/CD1, UL/CD2, UL/CD3 and SLES8.)
    </para>    
    <para>
      Upon boot, Linuxrc requires the presence of the boot directory (which
      contains the <filename>root</filename> file), the
      <filename>media.N</filename> directory and the
      <filename>content</filename> file. Having those files in the root of the
      source will insure that linuxrc can start the YaST installer.
    </para>
    <para>Once YaST has started, it will search the root of source for
      installation files using values from the <filename>content</filename>
      file name. However, to detect if multiple sources are involved, YaST
      first search for the
      <filename>order</filename> and <filename>instorder</filename> in the
      <filename>yast</filename> directory. The files in the  <filename>yast</filename> directory
      will reroute YaST and direct it to search for the installation files and
      media description in different locations than root of the source.
    </para>
    <para>
      On the installer source create a <filename>yast/order</filename> as described above
      and enter the location of the description data and
      packages. Alternativly, you can copy the description data of all sources to separate
      directories in the <filename>yast</filename> directory (This is the case
      on the SLES CD which contains the description data for UL to support
      multiple sources using CDs).
    </para>
    <para>
      In the 'order' example above, the 'order' directory structure
      looks as follows: 
    </para>
    <screen>
yast/
  instorder                     # instorder file 
  order                         # order file
  ul/                           # product 'ul', placing it below yast isn't really needed
                                # but practical.
    media.1/
      media                     # media ID for first CD
    content                     # content file, describing the paths
    UnitedLinux/
      setup/
        descr/
          *.sel
          packages
          packages.DU
          packages.en
          packages.de
          ...
          packages.pt
  sles8/
    media.1/
      media
    content
    suse/
      setup/
        descr/
          *.sel
          packages
          packages.DU
          packages.en
          packages.de
          ...
          packages.pt

    </screen>
    <para>
      YaST now takes this description instead of the one from the
      <emphasis>real</emphasis> media for the installation.      
      So when asking for a specific media, this media must match the
      <filename>media.1/media</filename>  file from the
      <emphasis>order</emphasis> directory.
      
    </para>
    <para>
      All dependencies (package or selection) are fulfilled by looking at
      all installation sources. If multiple sources provide a dependency,
      the source listed first in the 'order' file wins. (The installation
      order equals the installation priority currently). 
    </para>
 
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Example using SLES 8 and UnitedLinux 1.0 CDs</title>
    
    <para>
      You should at least copy the first CD from both UnitedLinux and SLES8
      sets, depending on what selection of software you want to install.      
    </para>
    <para>
      On the NFS server, create a directory which will serve as the
      installation source and make sure it is exported via NFS. This
      directory will be used later to specify the installation source using
      <command>linuxrc</command>.	  
    </para>
    <para>
      The following script illustrates what directories need to be created
      and where you should copy the data from the CDs. In this script, it
      is assumed that you have ISO images. In most cases you will have
      CDROMs instead. Do not use this script as provided. If you wish to
      use it, please make sure you have changed the directory names to
      something suitable to your environment.
    </para>

    <screen>
#!/bin/sh

instsource="/exports/sles8"
#
# Create CD directories
#
cd $instsource
mkdir -p sles8-i386/CD1
mkdir -p unitedlinux-i386/CD{1,2,3}

#
# Copy SLES CD
#
cd sles8-i386/CD1

mount -oloop /iso/SLES-8-i386-CD1.iso /mnt
cp -a /mnt/* .
umount /mnt

#
# back to root of source
#
cd ../..

#
# Copy UL CDs
#

# 1
cd unitedlinux-i386/CD1
mount -oloop /iso/UnitedLinux-1.0-i386-CD1.iso /mnt
cp -a /mnt/* .
umount /mnt

# 2
cd ../CD2
mount -oloop /iso/UnitedLinux-1.0-i386-CD2.iso /mnt
cp -a /mnt/* .
umount /mnt


# 3
cd ../CD3
mount -oloop /iso/UnitedLinux-1.0-i386-CD3.iso /mnt
cp -a /mnt/* .
umount /mnt

#
# back to root of source
#
cd ../..

#
# Now we have to symlink some data to make this
# a multiple source directory
#

# Then the boot directory with the installation image
# 
cp -a  sles8-i386/CD1/boot .


# The content file and the media directory
#
cp -a  sles8-i386/CD1/content .
cp -a  sles8-i386/CD1/media.1 .


# We are almost done..
# Now we'll adapt the order files.
# Fields of the order files are TAB delimited

mkdir -p yast

printf "/sles8-i386/CD1\t/sles8-i386/CD1" >  yast/order
printf "/unitedlinux-i386/CD1\t/unitedlinux-i386/CD1" >> yast/order

printf "/unitedlinux-i386/CD1\t/unitedlinux-i386/CD1"  > yast/instorder
printf "/sles8-i386/CD1\t/sles8-i386/CD1" >> yast/instorder

#
# End
#  

    </screen>        
    <para>After you have gone through all steps, you will have a structure
      similar to the one shown below.</para>
    <screen>
.
|-- sles8-i386
|   |-- boot
|   |-- docu
|   |-- media.1
|   |-- suse
|   `-- yast
|-- unitedlinux-i386
|   |-- CD1
|   |-- CD2
|   `-- CD3
|-- boot -> sles8-i386/boot
|-- media.1 -> sles8-i386/media.1
`-- yast

</screen>
    <para>And the root of the source will have the following content:</para>
<screen>

# ls -1

sles8-i386
unitedlinux-i386
boot
content
driverupdate
media.1
yast

</screen>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Network Installation with Service Packs</title>
    <section>
      <title>Installation using SP Kernel/Driverupdate</title>            
      <para>
	Other than containing  updated packages and fixed, service packs contain
	new boot kernels and  installation image fixes which should be used during installation instead
	of the original kernels. The installation kernel and the new installation
	files are all contained in the images used to create the CD and are
	located in the directory <filename>boot/loader</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
	If initialy  only the original packages from the released products are to
	be installed, the steps described above can used with the following
	changes:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The target system has to be booted using the kernels from the
	    service pack CDs, i.e. by booting using the SP CD directly or by
	    using a network bootable image built using the files
	    from <filename>boot/loader</filename> on the SP CD.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    On the source side, the file <filename>driverupdate</filename> must be
	    provided in the root of the source. This file is needed by
	    <command>linuxrc</command> to update the installation environment
	    with the latest patches and fixes.
	  </para>	
	</listitem>     
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	After installation is done, you can mount the first SP CD and execute
	the update scripts available there to update the packages on the
	system.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Service Pack full network installation</title>
      <note>
	<para>
	  Although this feature has been reported to be working by many, it
	  is not officially supported and some issues might arise.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Using this mothod without paying attention to details, wrong
	  packages might get installed which  in all cases will not cause
	  any harm, but the final installed system will have texts and instructions
	  pointing to the wrong product.
	</para>
      </note>

      
      <para>Service Pack 3 contains packages from both UL and SLES, and hence
	it has to be treated in a special way. To install SP3 packages during
	initial setup, all SP3 CDs have to be copied into a directory in the
	installation source. For example, you can create a directory named <emphasis>service-pack-3</emphasis>
	with two subdirectories for both SP3 CDs. After the CDs have been
	copied, the following structure should be available in the installation source:
      </para>
      <screen>
.
|-- sles8-i386
|   |-- boot
|   |-- docu
|   |-- media.1
|   |-- suse
|   `-- yast
|-- service-pack-3
|   |-- CD1
|   |-- CD2
|-- unitedlinux-i386
|   |-- CD1
|   |-- CD2
|   `-- CD3
|-- boot -> sles8-i386/boot
|-- media.1 -> sles8-i386/media.1
`-- yast

</screen>
      <para>
	To enable the service pack during installation, the
	<filename>order</filename> and <filename>instorder</filename> files in
	the the <filename>yast</filename> directory have to be changed.
      </para>
      <para>
	The file <filename>instorder</filename> should additionally have a
	pointer to the location of SP3, in this case:
      </para>
      <screen>
/unitedlinux-i386/CD1    /unitedlinux-i386/CD1
/sles8-i386/CD1   /sles8-i386/CD1
/service-pack-3/CD1      /service-pack-3/CD1
      </screen>
      <para>
	The file <filename>order</filename> will determine the priority for
	the packages to be installed. The service pack should have the heighest
	priority as it holds all updated packages. It also should appear before
	the SLES source because it holds updated SLES packages.
      </para>
      <screen>
/service-pack-3/CD1      /service-pack-3/CD1
/sles8-i386/CD1   /sles8-i386/CD1
/unitedlinux-i386/CD1    /unitedlinux-i386/CD1
      </screen>
    
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>SP3 Autoinstallation directly from SP CD image</title>
      <para>
	Another alternative to adding SP3 as an additional source exisit. This
	requires executing a script at the end of the installation which mounts
	a remote file system containing the image of the SP3 CD and calling the
	update scripts available on the SP CD or calling any other script to
	update the packages.
      </para>
      <para>Such a script can be called in the post-install phase, and can
	consist of the following steps:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Mount the remote file system</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Call one of the scripts available on the SP CD,
	    i.e. <filename>install_update_rpms.sh</filename>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Schedule the system for reboot after the installation and
	    update of the packages is done, i.e. with <command>at</command>.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Known Issues</title>
      <section>
	<title>Product for Online Update</title>
	<para>
	  When installing using this method, the online update, YOU, will fail
	  to report the right product. YOU reads the product data from the
	  directory <filename>/var/adm/YaST/ProdDB</filename> and takes the
	  last product description file available in the directory if multiple
	  sources were used to install the system.	  
	</para>
	<para>
	  If the system is being autoinstalled, the order of the product files
	  can be changed using  a post-install script, otherwise they have to
	  be changed manually.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>


