  <appendix id="multiplesources">
    <title>Creating NFS directory for UL/SLES from distribution CDs</title>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>
	UnitedLinux defines a core set of packages which implement the UnitedLinux runtime environment.
      All tests, certifications, and applications are based on this set of packages
      which should not be altered in any way. The ideal way to guarantee
      unaltered data, is providing it on CD-ROM.
    </para>
    <para>
    However, this makes including (vendor specific) extensions and bug-fixes on
    the same media impossible. A separate media must be supplied for
    installation.
    </para>
    <para>
      The 'multiple source' approach of YaST gives a solution as it allows
      installation from several (package) sources. So a customer can start
      installing from the original UnitedLinux CDs, proceed with a product CD,
      and end with a patch CD containing the latest security patches.
    </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>
	Installation workflow
      </title>

      <section>
	<title>
	  The installer source
	</title>
	<para>
	When starting the installation from a media (CD, DVD, NFS, ...), linuxrc looks
	for a /boot/root file containing a complete (cramfs based) root-fs for
	YaST.</para>

	<para>	Usually, this file is on the boot CD, but other installation types are
	also supported by linuxrc. The information, where the /boot/root file
	came from, is passed to YaST and defines the installer source. 
	
	</para>
	<para>	YaST now looks at this installer source for a /yast/order file. If this
	file exists, YaST goes into the 'multiple installation' mode.
	</para>
	<para>	In this mode, the source description (information about the packages) is on
	the installer source and the source data (the rpm packages itself) is
	on separate media.
	</para>
	<para>
	  If the order file does not exist, YaST does not separate the source
	description from the source data and both must reside on the same
	media. (The latter is what happens if you boot the first UnitedLinux
	CD.)
	</para>
      </section>
 
      <section>
	<title>
	  The order file
	</title>

	<para> The order file defines which sources are needed for installation and their priority for installation.
	  A typical example for an order file is given here:
	</para>
<screen>
# yast/order: priority of installation sources
#
# source-       product
# description   path
/yast/sles8     /sles8-i386/CD1
/yast/ul        /unitedlinux-i386/CD1
/               /
</screen>

	<para> The order file is ASCII, line based, '#' at the beginning of a line denote a comment line.</para>

	<para> Each non-comment line should contain two (whitespace separated) directory specifications. If the second one is omitted, it defaults to "/".</para>

	<para> The first directory specifies the location of the description.
 The second directory specifies the location of the product as defined here.
 For CD/DVD bases products, this is usually "/". But for network installations, or if several product are placed on a single CD, each product needs a separate path.
 You can even specify a full URL (e.g. "nfs://my-nfs-server.domain.org/product/CD1") in the second column. 
During installation, you can't switch the type of media. If your installer source is CD, every other source must be CD based. If your installer source is NFS, every other source is expected to be on the same NFS server.</para>
	<para>
 
In the above example of the order file, note the last line being "/". This means the last of the three installation sources is on the same media as the installer.
 


	</para>
	</section>
      <section>
	<title>
	The instorder file
	</title>
	<para>
	  As stated above, the<filename> /yast/order</filename> file lists the sources in priority
	  order. So a package from a source listed earlier in this file
	  overrides a package (of the same name) from a later source. This
	  technique is used to override the yast2-translation packages from
	  unitedlinux-i386 (where all help texts refer to UnitedLinux) with
	  yast2-translation packages from sles8-i386 (where all help texts
	  refer to SuSE Linux).</para>
	<para>
 
	  But the <filename>/yast/order</filename> also defines the installation order, which might not be wanted when the 'base' packages are on a lower-priority source
	  This is where <filename>/yast/instorder</filename> comes into play. This defines the installation
	  order by repeating the entries of the first column of /yast/order in
	  the right order.</para>

 

	<para>A typical example for an instorder file is given here:</para>
	<screen>
# yast/instorder: order of installation sources
#
# install 'ul' before 'sles8'
#
/yast/ul
/yast/sles8
/
</screen>
      </section>
      <section>

	<title>Setting it all up</title>

	<para> Combining multiple sources requires that all sources comply to
	  the UnitedLinux media description standard.</para>

 
	<para>On the installer source create a <filename>yast/order</filename> as described above
	    and copy the description data of all sources to separate
	    directories. List these directories in the order file and check for
	    conflicting package (.rpm) or selection (.sel) names.
	</para>
	<para>
	    If names conflict, the name coming 'first' in the order file wins.
	  </para>

 
	  <para>In the 'order' example above, the 'order' directory structure
	    looks as follows: </para>
	  <screen>
yast/
  instorder                     # instorder file 
  order                         # order file
  ul/                           # product 'ul', placing it below yast isn't really needed
                                # but practical.
    media.1/
      media                     # media ID for first CD
    content                     # content file, describing the paths
    UnitedLinux/
      setup/
        descr/
          *.sel
          packages
          packages.DU
          packages.en
          packages.de
          ...
          packages.pt
  sles8/
    media.1/
      media
    content
    suse/
      setup/
        descr/
          *.sel
          packages
          packages.DU
          packages.en
          packages.de
          ...
          packages.pt

</screen>



	  <para>
	    YaST now takes this description instead of the one from the 'real' media for the installation.
	    So when asking for a specific media, this media must match the media.1/media
	    file from the <emphasis>order</emphasis> directory.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    All dependencies (package or selection) are fulfilled by looking at
	    all installation sources. If multiple sources provide a dependency,
	    the source listed first in the 'order' file wins.

	    (The installation order equals the installation priority currently). 
	  </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Example using SLES 8 and UnitedLinux 1.0 CDs</title>
     
	<para>
	  You should at least copy the first CD from both UnitedLinux and SLES
	  8 sets, depending on what selection of software you want to install.
	</para>
	<para>
	  On the NFS server, create a directory which will serve as the
	  installation source and make sure it is exported via NFS. This
	  directory will be used later to specify the installation source using
	  linuxrc.	  
	</para>
	<para>
	  The following script illustrates what directories need to be created
	  and where you should copy the data from the CDs. In this script, it
	  is assumed that you have ISO images. In most cases you will have
	CDROMs instead. Do not use this script as provided. If you wish to
	use it, please make sure you have changed the directory names to
	something suitable to your environment.
	</para>

	<screen>
#!/bin/sh

instsource="/exports/sles8"
#
# Create CD directories
#
cd $instsource
mkdir -p sles8-i386/CD1
mkdir unitedlinux-i386/CD{1,2,3}

#
# Copy SLES CD
#
cd sles8-i386/CD1

mount -oloop /iso/SLES-8-i386-CD1.iso /mnt
cp -a /mnt/* .
umount /mnt

cd ../..

#
# Copy UL CDs
#

# 1
cd unitedlinux-i386/CD1
mount -oloop /iso/UnitedLinux-1.0-i386-CD1.iso /mnt
cp -a /mnt/* .
umount /mnt

# 2
cd ../CD2
mount -oloop /iso/UnitedLinux-1.0-i386-CD2.iso /mnt
cp -a /mnt/* .
umount /mnt


# 3
cd ../CD3
mount -oloop /iso/UnitedLinux-1.0-i386-CD3.iso /mnt
cp -a /mnt/* .
umount /mnt

#
# back to root of source
#
cd ../..

#
# Now we have to move some data around to make this
# a multiple source directory
#
# first we copy the order directory described above.

cp -a sles8-i386/CD1/yast .

#
# Then the boot directory with the installation image
# 
cp -a sles8-i386/CD1/boot .

#
# The content file and the media directory
#
cp sles8-i386/CD1/content .
cp -a sles8-i386/CD1/media.1 .


#
# Now we copy the description files from SLES to the order directory as
# described earlier.
#
mkdir -p yast/sles8/suse/setup/descr
cp -a sles8-i386/CD1/suse/setup/descr yast/sles8/suse/setup
cp  sles8-i386/CD1/content  yast/sles8/
cp -a sles8-i386/CD1/media.1 yast/sles8/

#
# We are almost done..
# Now we'll adapt the order files.
# Fields of the order files are TAB delimited

cat << EOF > yast/order
/yast/sles8      /sles8-i386/CD1
/yast/ul         /unitedlinux-i386/CD1
EOF

cat << EOF > yast/instorder
/yast/ul         /unitedlinux-i386/CD1
/yast/sles8      /sles8-i386/CD1
EOF



#
# End
#  

	</screen>
	<note>
	  <para>
	    Fields of the order files have TAB as delimiter.
	  </para>
	</note>
   
      
	
    </section>

  </appendix>



  <!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: xml
  sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "chapter")
  End:
  -->