<chapter id="Bootmanagement">
  <title>Network Based Installation</title>        
  <para>
    The installation method using AutoYaST provides a way to automatically
    and identically install groups of systems. The first step when preparing
    AutoYaST installations is deciding how you want the systems at your
    site to be installed. For example, the following scenario would be ideal to
    set up and perform automated installations:

  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	You need to install SuSE Linux on 50 new systems.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	The development department owns 30 out of the 50 new dual processor
	and SCSI systems, and its systems must be installed as clients with
	development software.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	The sales department owns 20 out of the 50 new, uni-processor IDE
	based systems and its systems must be installed as clients with end user
	software and office tools.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>
    Prerequisites:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>A boot server on the same Ethernet segment</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>An install server with the SuSE Linux OS</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>An AutoYaST configuration server that defines rules and profiles.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <!-- FIXME: Add info about boot server and installation server -->

  <section>
    <title>Configuration Server</title>
    <para>
      A configuration repository holds the control files for multiple
      machines. The control files can have any file names, which have to
      specified at the boot time of a client. To avoid supplying the
      profile name for every client, you can only define the directory of
      the control files. If a directory is specified, then the client tries
      to load a file with a name matching it's IP address in HEX
      mode.  This has the advantage that you will be dealing with
      consistent file names rather than IPs as file names which might lead to
      some confusion.
    </para>
    <para>
      The configuration repository is the same directory you have to define
      if you are using the configuration system for creating control files.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>&http; Repository</title>
      <para>
	To be able to use the &http; protocol to retrieve control file while
	auto-installing, you need a working &http; server on the server
	side. Install <emphasis>Apache</emphasis> or your favorite web
	server and enable it using &yast2;. Normally the the web server root
	directory resides in <filename>/srv/www/htdocs</filename>
	so you need to create a subdirectory below the root directory of
	the web server which will be your configuration repository.
      </para>
      
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>&nfs; Repository</title>
      <para>
	Create a directory and make it available via &nfs; to the clients by
	exporting it. This directory may for example be in the same place
	where you have copied the CDs. (i.e. <filename>/usr/local/SuSE</filename>)
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>	
      <title>&tftp; Repository</title>
      <para>
	By default the &tftp; directory is available under
	<filename>/tftpboot</filename> which can also contain boot images
	if you are booting over network. Do not forget to enable TFTP in
	the Inetd configuration file
	(<filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename>). <emphasis>Inetd</emphasis> configuration can be
	done using &yast2;.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>








      <!--
       Local Variables:
       mode: xml
       sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "chapter")
       End:
      -->
