  <PART>
  <TITLE>Preparing for Auto-Installation</TITLE>
  <PARTINTRO>
    <TITLE>Getting Started</TITLE>
    <para>
      Depending on the installation environment, hardware settings and the
      complexity of the configuration certain preparations have to take place
      before any installation can take place.
    </para>
    <sect1>
      <title>
	Examine if auto-installation is actually a solution for you
      </title>
      <para>
	Installing a single client in an interactive way using  &company-suse;  is only a
	couple of clicks away. So if you intention is to install only  a small
	number of systems which differ in hardware and configuration maybe it
	is faster to install them the traditional way.
      </para>
      <para>
	Auto-Installation gets to be interesting when installing large number
	of machines which at least have one thing in common. For example
	auto-installation can be used for installing a network of workstation
	which share the same environemnt and have similar hardware.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Collect information</title>
      <para>
	You need to collect information about the machines to be
	installed. This includes hardware and network information. Please make
	sure you know the following about the machines you want to install:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Hard disk types and sizes</para>	  
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Graphic interface and attached monitor if any</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Network insterface and MAC address if know</para>
	</listitem>	
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	With these parameters you are ready to go and create a control file
	to control the auto-installation process.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Create the control file</title>
      <para>
	To create a control file  you either can use the configuration
	system which covers most of the features of the auto-installation
	system or you can use your favourite editor. In some cases you may need
	to add some information manually after creating the control file with
	the configuration system
      </para>
      <para>
	After creating the control file, make sure it  has a valid syntax. The
	easy way to check the syntax is by using some tools already available
	on the distribution. For example to verfiy that the file is well
	formed, use the utility <command>tidy</command> from the package with
	the same name.
      </para>
      <screen>
	tidy -xml &lt;control file&gt;
      </screen>
      <para>
	If the control file is not well formed, i.e. if a tag is not closed,
	tidy will have an output similar to the following:
      </para>
      <screen>
	<![CDATA[
	line 11 column 3 - Warning: unexpected </pre-scripts> in <script>
	line 12 column 2 - Warning: unexpected </configure> in <script>
	line 13 column 1 - Warning: unexpected </profile> in <script>
	This document has errors that must be fixed before
	using HTML Tidy to generate a tidied up version.
	]]>
      </screen>
      <para>
	Before going on with the auto-installation, please fix any errors
	resulting from such checks. The auto-installation process can't be
	started with  non-well formed control files.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>
	Decide how you wish to boot the target system.
      </title>
      <para>
	A target system can be booted in different ways. Booting the machine
	and initiating the auto-installation process is as important as the
	installation itself. Depending on how many target systems you wish to
	install, the following methods are supported:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Floppy</para>
	  <para>Not recommended in complex network environments. A Floppy
	    nowadays can't hold all necessary information needed to setup a
	    machine for installation. A Floppy  should only be used in very
	    special cases and if it is used, the default boot floppy compenents
	    supplied with  &company-suse;  must be modifed to match you exact needs.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    However, the floppy can be used to store the control file and other
	    information needed for installation.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>CD-ROM</para>
	  <para>
	    You can use the original  &company-suse;  CD-ROMs in compenation with other
	    media, i.e. with a floppy to hold the control file or in compenation
	    with network where the control file can be located.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    It is also possible to create customized CD-ROMs to hold only the
	    package you need in addition to the control file which also can be
	    saved on the CD-ROM. This method requires creation of CD-ROMs
	    everytime you wish to change the configuration though.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Network
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Using the network to boot a target system is the most
	    convinient way for auto-installing. Booting over the network and
	    holding a repository of control files on an accessible server can
	    be very flexible especially when configuring different types of
	    system with different roles and hardware.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </partintro>

  &Profile;
  &CreateProfile;
  &ConfigurationManagement;
  
  &Bootmanagement;
  </PART>
      <!--
       Local Variables:
       mode: xml
       sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "part")
       End:
      -->