
<chapter>
    <title>Rules and Classes</title>
  <section>
    <title>Rule based auto-installation</title>

    <para>
      After you decide how you want the systems at your site to be installed,
      the most important step when preparing automated installations is to
      create the essential files that are used during auto-installation: the
      rules.xml file  and a profile for
      each group of systems. The rules file is a xml based file that should contain 
      rules for each group of systems (or single systems) that you want to
      automatically install. A set of rules distinguish a group of systems based on
      one or more system attributes, and at the end it links each group to a profile, which
      is a XML based file that defines how the Linux software will be installed on
      each system in the group. Both the rules file and the profiles must be
      located in a user defined directory.
    </para>
    <para>
      If more than one rule apply, the final profile for each group is generated
      on the fly using a merge script. The merging process is based on the
      order of the rules and later rules override configuration data in earlier rules.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is also possible to perform a standard installation without any
      rules. If the rules file is not found, system installation proceeds in the
      classic way by just using the supplied profile or by searching for the
      profile depending on the <emphasis>MAC</emphasis> or
      <emphasis>IP</emphasis> addresses of 
      the system.     
    </para>
<!--
    <para>
      In the previous scenario, you would create a rules file with two different
      rules, one rule for the development and another rule for the sales
      department. For each rule, you could use different system parameters to
      distinguish the groups from one another: the development department has SMP
      and SCI  based systems and the sales group has IDE based systems. Each rule
      would also contain a link to an appropriate profile. For example, in the
      rule for the development department, you would add a link to the profile, called
      <filename>devel.xml</filename>, that you created for this department. And, in the rule
      for the sales department, you would add a link to the profile, called
      <filename>sales.xml</filename>, that you created for the sales department.
    </para>
-->

  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Classes</title>
    
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mixing Rules and Classes</title>
    
  </section>
</chapter>

      <!--
       Local Variables:
       mode: xml
       sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "book" "chapter")
       End:
      -->
