      <section id="choosingbootmedia">
	<title>Choosing the right Boot Medium</title>
	<para>
	  There are different methods for booting the client. The computer can boot from
	  its network interface card (NIC) to receive the boot images via  &dhcp; /TFTP. Or a suitable kernel as well as an initrd image are loaded from a
	  floppy or a bootable CD-ROM. 
	</para>
	<section id="bootfromfloppy">
	  <title>
	    Booting from a floppy
	  </title>
	  <para>
	    For testing/rescue purposes or because the NIC does not have a PROM or PXE,
	    you can build a boot floppy to use with &autoyast2;. Using a floppy
	    to initiate an auto-install process is limited due to the size of the
	    data a floppy can hold. However, it is still  possible to use
	    floppies when auto-installing a single, disconnected machine.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Floppies can be used to store the control file, especially when using
	    the original  &company-suse;  CD-ROMs for a single, disconnected machine. Using the
	    kernel command line, you can specify the location of the control
	    file on the floppy. (See <quote><xref linkend='BootFromFloppy'
		endterm="BootFromFloppy.title"></xref></quote>)
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Even without specifying any command line options, it is still possible to initiate the
	    auto-install process by placing a control file on a floppy with a
	    special, pre-defined file name (<filename>autoinst.xml</filename>). &yast2; will check for
	    <filename>autoinst.xml</filename> upon startup. If it finds the file, &yast2; switches from interactive to automated installation.
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="bootfromcd">
	  <title>Booting from CD-ROM</title>
	  <para>
	    You can use the original  &company-suse;  CD-ROMs in combination with other
	    media, i.e. with a floppy to hold the control file. Alternatively, save the control file via the network interface on a remote machine.
	  </para><remark>emap 2011-11-04: I'm surprised there's still mention of floppies but not a word about USB sticks, etc.</remark>
	  <para>
	    It is also possible to create customized CD-ROMs to hold only the
	    package you need in addition to the control file which also can be
	    saved on the CD-ROM. This method requires creation of new CD-ROMs
	    every time you wish to change the configuration.
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>
 
      <!--
       Local Variables:
       mode: xml
       sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast2.xml" "chapter" "section")
       End:
      --> 
