<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % images SYSTEM "images.ent">
%images;

<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities/en.ent">
%entities;

<!-- Examples -->
<!ENTITY % examples SYSTEM "examples.ent">
%examples;

<!-- components -->
<!ENTITY % components SYSTEM "components.ent">
%components;

]>

  <section id="createprofile.completeconf">
    <title>Adding Complete Configurations</title>
    <para>
      For many applications and services you might have prepared a
      configuration file which should be copied to the appropriate
      location in the installed system, for example if you are
      installing a web server and have a <emphasis>ready to go</emphasis>
      server configuration file (<filename>httpd.conf</filename>).
    </para>
    <para>
      Using this resource, you can embed the file into the control file by
      specifying the final path on the installed system. &yast; will copy this
      file to the specified location.
    </para>
    <para>
      This feature requires the autoyast2 package to be installed. If the package is
      missing, &ay; will silently ignore the <emphasis>files</emphasis> section.
      Since openSUSE 11.1 and SLES11, &ay; will install the package automatically if
      it is missing.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since openSUSE 11.1 and SLES11, you can specify the <emphasis>file_location</emphasis>
      where the file should be retrieved from. For an HTTP server this would
      look like: <emphasis>&lt;file_location&gt;http://my.server.site/issue&lt;/file_location&gt;</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since openSUSE 11.2 (not SLES11), you can create directories by specifying a <emphasis>file_path</emphasis> that ends with a slash.
    </para>
    &example.files;

    <para>
      A more advanced example is shown below. This configuration will create a
      file using the content supplied in <emphasis>file_contents</emphasis>
      and change the permissions and ownership of the file. After the file has
      been copied to the system, a script is executed, which can be used to
      manipulate the file and prepare it for the environment of the client.
    </para>
    &example.filesadv;
  </section>

