<chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    
    <para>
      &ay;2 is a system for installing one or more SUSE Linux systems
      automatically and without user intervention. &ay;2; installations
      are performed using  an &ay; profile with installation and configuration
      data. That profile can be created using the configuration insterface
      of &ay;2; and can be  provided to &yast;2 during installation in
      different ways.
    </para>  

    <section id="avail">
      <title>Availability</title>
      <para>
	&ay;2; is available with recent SUSE products starting
	from SUSE Linux 8.0 and business products starting from SLES 8.
      </para>
      <para>Products prior to SuSE Linux 8.0 and business products based
	on SLES 7 have an auto-installation
	system based on Y&yast;1. A configuration management
	system is provided by ALICE for these products.
      </para>
      <note>
	<title>Updated documentation</title>
	<para>Updated documentation can always be found at the following URL:
	  <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/~ug">http://www.suse.com/~ug</ulink></para>
      </note>
    </section>


    <section id="motiv">
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <para>
	The <ulink url="http://www.linuxjournal.com/">Linux Journal</ulink>, in
	an article in <ulink
	  url="http://www.linuxjournal.com/categories.php?op=newindex&amp;catid=178">issue 78</ulink> writes:
      </para>
      <para>
	<quote>
	  A standard Linux installation asks many questions about what to
	  install, what hardware to configure, how to configure the network
	  interface, etc. Answering these questions once is informative and maybe
	  even fun. But imagine a system engineer who has to set up a new Linux
	  network with a large number of machines. Now, the same issues need to
	  be addressed and the same questions answered repeatedly. This makes the
	  task very inefficient, not to mention a source of irritation and
	  boredom. Hence, a need arises to automate this parameter and option
	  selection.</quote>
      </para>
      <para>
	<quote>The thought of simply copying the hard disks naturally crosses one's
	  mind. This can be done quickly, and all the necessary functions and
	  software will be copied without option selection. However, the fact is
	  that simple copying of hard disks causes the individual computers to
	  become too similar. This, in turn, creates an altogether new mission of
	  having to reconfigure the individual settings on each PC. For example,
	  IP addresses for each machine will have to be reset. If this is not
	  done properly, strange and inexplicable behavior results.</quote>
      </para>

      <para>
	Regular installation of SuSE Linux is semi-automated by default. The user is
	requested to select the necessary information at the beginning of the
	installation (In most cases language only), &yast;2 then  generates a
	proposal for the underlying system depending on different factors and
	system paramters. In
	most cases, and especially for new systems, such a proposal  can be
	used to install the system and provides a usable installation.
      </para>
      <para>
	The steps following the proposal are fully automated and the user is only
	prompted at the end of the installation to configure hardware and network services.
      </para>
      <para>
	&ay;2; can be used where no user intervention is required or
	where customization is required. Using  an &ay; profile, &yast;2
	prepares the system for a custom installation and avoids any
	interaction with the user, unless specified in the file 
	controling the installation.
      </para>
      <para>
	&ay;2; is not an automated GUI system. This means that in most
	cases many screen will be skipped, i.e. you will never see the language
	selection interface. &ay;2; will simply pass the language
	parameter to the sub-system without displaying any language related
	interface.
      </para>
      
       </section>

    <section id="overviewandconcept">
      <title>Overview and Concept</title>
      <para>
	Using &ay;2;, multiple systems sharing the same environment and
	similar but not necesserily identical hardware and performing similar
	tasks, can easily be installed in parallel and quickly. A
	configuration file&mdash; referred to as "&ay; profile"&mdash; is created using
	existing configuration resources. The profile file can be easily
	tailored for any specific environment. 
      </para>
      
      
      <para>
	Unlike autoinstallation systems available with older SUSE
	releases, &ay;2; is fully integrated and provides various options for
	installing and configuring a system. The main advantage over older
	systems and other auto-installation systems is the possibility to configure a
	computer by using existing modules and avoiding using custom scripts which
	are normally executed at the end of the installation.
      </para>

      <para>
      This document will guide you through the three steps of auto-installation:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Preparation: All relevant information about the target system are
	    collected and turned into the appropriate directives of the profile.
	    The profile file is transferred onto the target system where
	    its directives will be parsed and transformed to &yast;2 conforming
	    data. </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Installation: Follows the instructions given in the profile and
	    installs the base system.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Configuration: &yast;2 in addition to user-defined post-install
	    scripts, complete the system configuration.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	The complete and detailed process is illustrated in the following figure:
      </para>
      
      <?anas-pagebreak?>
      <figure id="process">
	<title id="process.title">Auto-installation process</title>
	<mediaobject>&ay;-oview;</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    
  </chapter>



  <!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: xml
  sgml-parent-document: ("autoyast.xml" "book" "book")
  End:
  -->



