<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % images SYSTEM "images.ent">
%images;

<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities/en.ent">
%entities;

<!-- Examples -->
<!ENTITY % examples SYSTEM "examples.ent">
%examples;

<!-- components -->
<!ENTITY % components SYSTEM "components.ent">
%components;

]>
  <section id="CreateProfile.Network">
    <title>
      Network Configuration
    </title>

    <section id="Configuration.Network.Devices">
      <title>
	Network Devices, DNS and Routing.
      </title>
      <para>
	Network configuration is used to connect a single  &company-suse;  Linux
	workstation to an Ethernet-based LAN or to configure a dial-up
	connection. More complex configurations (multiple network cards,
	routing, etc.) are also provided. With this module it is possible to
	configure and setup Ethernet controllers and Token-Ring controllers.
      </para>
      <para>
	In the networking section, set this option to "true" (default is
	"false", available since openSUSE 11.2 but not in SLES11):
      </para>
    <screen>
        &lt;keep_install_network config:type=&quot;boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/keep_install_network&gt;
    </screen>
    <para>
    &yast; will keep network settings created during installation (via Linuxrc) 
    and/or merge it with network settings from the &ay; profile (if defined).
    &ay; settings have higher priority than already present configuration files. 
    &yast; will write ifcfg-* files from profile without removing old ones. 
    If there is an empty or no dns and routing section, &yast; will keep already present values. Otherwise settings from the profile will be applied.
      </para>
      <para>
	To configure network settings and activate networking automatically,
	one global resource is used to store the whole network configuration.
      </para>
      
      &example.network;
    </section>

    <section id="Configuration.Network.Proxy">
      <title>
	Proxy
      </title>
      <para>
	Configure your Internet proxy (caching) settings.
      </para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>HTTP proxy</emphasis> is the name of the proxy server for your access to the world wide web (WWW).
	<emphasis>FTP proxy</emphasis> is the name of the proxy server for your access to the file transfer services (FTP).
	<emphasis>No proxy</emphasis> domains<remark>emap 2011-11-06: Does 'domains' belong here? Delete or put within 'emphasis' tag?</remark> is a list of domains for
	which requests should be carried out directly without caching.
      </para>
      <para>
	If you are using a proxy server with authorization, fill in Proxy user name and Proxy password.
      </para>
      <example>
	<title>
	  Network configuration: Proxy
	</title>
	<screen>
  <xi:include href="examples/example.proxy.xml" parse="text"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>	  
	  </screen>
	</example>

      
    </section>
    <section id="Configuration.Network.Inetd">
      <title>(X)Inetd </title>

      <para>
	The profile has elements to specify which superserver should be
	used (netd_service), whether it should be enabled (netd_status) and
	how the services should be configured (netd_conf).
      </para>
      <para>
	A service description element has two parts: key and non-key. When
	writing the configuration, services are matched using the key fields;
	to the matching service, non-key fields are applied. If no service
	matches, it is created. If more services match, a warning is
	reported. The key fields are <emphasis>script, service, protocol and
	server.</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>service</emphasis> and <emphasis>protocol</emphasis> are
	matched literally. <emphasis>script</emphasis> is the base name of the
	config file: usually a file in<filename> /etc/xinetd.d</filename>, for
	example "echo-udp", or "inetd.conf". For compatibility with 8.2,
	<emphasis>server</emphasis> is matched more loosely: if it is
	<filename>/usr/sbin/tcpd</filename>, the real server name is taken
	from <emphasis>server_args</emphasis>. After that, the basename of the
	first whitespace-separated word is taken and these values are
	compared.
      </para>
      &example.inetd;

    </section>
  </section>

