<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % images SYSTEM "images.ent">
%images;

<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities/en.ent">
%entities;

<!-- Examples -->
<!ENTITY % examples SYSTEM "examples.ent">
%examples;

<!-- components -->
<!ENTITY % components SYSTEM "components.ent">
%components;

]>


  <section id="CreateProfile.Security">
    <title>
      Security settings
    </title>
    
    <para>
      Using the features of this module, you will be able to change the local
      security settings on the target system. The local security settings
      include the boot configuration, login settings, password settings,
      user addition settings, and file permissions.
    </para>
    <para>
      Configuring the security settings automatically corresponds to the
      <emphasis>Custom Settings</emphasis> in the security module available in
      the running system which lets you create your own, customized
      configuration.
    </para>      
    
    &example.security;
    <section>
      <title>Password Settings Options</title>
      <para>
	Change various password settings. These settings are mainly stored in the <filename>/etc/login.defs</filename> file.
      </para>
      <para>
	Use this resource to activate one of  the <emphasis>encryption</emphasis> methods currently supported.
	If not set, <emphasis>DES</emphasis> is configured.
      </para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>DES</emphasis>, the Linux default method, works in all
	network environments, but it restricts you to passwords no longer than
	eight characters. <emphasis>MD5</emphasis> allows longer passwords,
	thus provides more security, but some network protocols don't support
	this, and you may have problems with NIS. <emphasis>Blowfish</emphasis>
	is also supported.
      </para>
      <para>Additionally, you can setup the system to check for password
	plausibility and length etc.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Boot Settings</title>
      <para>
	Use the security resource, you can change various boot settings.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>How to interpret Ctrl + Alt + Del</emphasis></para>
	  <para>When someone at the console has pressed the CTRL + ALT + DEL key combination, the system usually reboots. Sometimes it is desirable to ignore this event, for example, when the system serves as both workstation and server.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>Shutdown behavior of KDM</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Set who is allowed to shut down the machine from KDM.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Login Settings</title>
      <para>Change various login settings. These settings are mainly stored in the '/etc/login.defs' file.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>New user settings (useradd settings)</title>
      <para>Set the minimum and maximum possible user ID and set the minimum
	and maximum possible group ID.
      </para>
    </section>
    
  </section>

